<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The policy and government of the Venetians both in civil and military affairs / written in French by the Sieur de la Hay, and faithfully Englished.</title>
            <author>La Haye, Sieur de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1671</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L180A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230570</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27246944</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27246944</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110049</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48274)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110049)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1723:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The policy and government of the Venetians both in civil and military affairs / written in French by the Sieur de la Hay, and faithfully Englished.</title>
                  <author>La Haye, Sieur de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 196 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Starkey ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London,</pubPlace>
                  <date>1671.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and tightly bound, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Venice (Italy) --  History --  1508-1797.</term>
               <term>Venice (Italy) --  Politics and government --  1508-1797.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110049:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE POLICY AND GOVERNMENT OF THE Venetians, Both in Civil and Military Affairs.</p>
            <p>Written in French by the <hi>Sieur de la Hay,</hi> and Faithfully Engliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Starkey,</hi> at the <hi>Miter</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> 1671.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:110049:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110049:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:110049:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110049:3"/>
            <head>The Table of Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Firſt Book.</hi> Of their Civil Policy.</head>
               <item>OF the Foundation of <hi>Venice. page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 1.</label> Of the Duke. <hi>page 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 2.</label> Of the Counſel of Ten. <hi>page 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 3.</label> Of the Sages Grands. <hi>page 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 4.</label> Of their Procurators. <hi>page 34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 5.</label> Of their Podeſtats. <hi>page 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 6.</label> Of their Camerlingues. <hi>page 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 7.</label> Of their Ambaſſadors. <hi>page 46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 8.</label> Of the Nobility of this Commonwealth. <hi>page 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 9.</label> Of their Ladies. <hi>page 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:110049:4"/>
                  <label>Chap. 10.</label> Of their Citizens. <hi>page 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 11.</label> Of the Nobles upon <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra-firma. page 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 12.</label> A particular Diſcourſe upon ſome of their Maximes. <hi>page 90</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Second Book.</hi> Of their Military Policy.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 1.</label> Of the Venetian Militia in general. <hi>page 97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 2.</label> Of their Generaliſſimo. <hi>page 100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 3.</label> Of the General of the Gulf. <hi>page 109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 4.</label> Of the General of their Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſſes and their Governours. <hi>page 114</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 5.</label> Of the General of the Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Captains under his Command. <hi>page 119</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 6.</label> Of the Sur-Comites of the Gallies. <hi>page 122</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:110049:4"/>
                  <label>Chap. 7.</label> Of the General, or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Candia. page 129</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 8.</label> Of the General of <hi>Dalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. page 133</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 9.</label> Of the Grand-Captains. <hi>page 137</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 10.</label> Of their Forreign Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals. <hi>page 145</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 11.</label> Of the Forreign General in <hi>Dalmatia. page 147</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 12.</label> Of the General of the Forces drawn out of the Fleet upon occaſion. <hi>page 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 13.</label> Of the Governour of <hi>Candia. page 156</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 14.</label> Of Reflexions in manner of a Recapitulation. <hi>page 158</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 15.</label> Of their Armies in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. <hi>page 162</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 16.</label> Of their Cavalry. <hi>page 166</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 17.</label> Of their Light Horſe. <hi>page 172</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 18.</label> Of their Infantry. <hi>page 177</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Chap. 19.</label> Of their general Rules and Maximes in War. <hi>page 188</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:110049:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110049:5"/>
            <head>THE POLICY AND GOVERNMENT OF THE VENETIAN, Both in Civil and Military Affairs.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Introduction. Of the Foundation of <hi>Venice.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Uring the Wars of <hi>Attila,</hi> that <hi>Flagellum Dei,</hi> (as he was uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called) there being no refuge or ſanctuary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainſt the fury of his Arms, the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110049:6"/>demoliſhment of Towns, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of Countreys, the ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and blazing of whole Provinces ſet on fire on all ſides by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of his inſulting <hi>Barbarians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but a paſtime and recreation to his tyranny, he left behind him no other monuments of his victories where-ever he came, but horror and diſpair.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aquileia</hi> being a Town more than ordinarily conſiderable, had a greater ſhare than ordinary of the calamities of the War, and the miſerable remainder of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants which had ſurviv'd them, chooſing rather to expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the infidelity of the Sea, than once more to fall into his mercileſs hands, having imbark'd themſelves upon the <hi>Adriatick</hi> in ſuch lamentable Veſſels as their condition could ſupply, they ſail'd up and down for ſome time, but at
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110049:6"/>length growing weary, and unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with their wandring, they landed upon certain little Iſlands, and laid the foundation of the moſt honourable Republick in the World. Their firſt accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was Hurts, or Cabbins which they built, and ſetled themſelves in them when they had done, though not without great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for having conſum'd the ſmall ſtock of proviſions they brought along with them, they found themſelves under a neceſſity of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up ſome trade, and profeſſion, for their ſubſiſtance. Fiſhing and Navigation appearing to them the moſt proper, they embrac't them with both arms, and trading into the neighbouring Countrey they gain'd a reputation by degrees ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to their Traffick and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize. Their Comportment from the firſt was with ſo much
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110049:7"/>amity and concord, that their manner of living alluring all ſuch as had converſation with them, their little Iſlands were grown inſenſibly full of People ſubmitting to their Government, who by little and little form'd themſelves into a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that is now become conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable both for its grandure, and policy.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as thoſe who outliv'd the deſtruction of their Countrey, were of a mixt conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conſiſting both of Nobility and Commons; to cement their Eſtate, and make it more durable they agreed to have their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment mixt too, in which the No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bility were to be the chief, but with ſuch coherence and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the Commons, they ſhould do nothing without them To take away all pretence of Emu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation, it was concluded that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:110049:7"/>Citizens and Gentlemen indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently ſhould be habited in the ſame faſhion, which has been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd through ſo many Ages, to this very day; it was ordain'd alſo they ſhould all of them wear a certain Bonnet of black Wool, (which they call <hi>Barrett</hi>) with a fringe of the ſame ſtuff about it, to put them in mind of their former condition, and rebate the edge of their pride, to which otherwiſe, young and capricious People (as they were) might be too prone, and propenſe.</p>
            <p>But envy and virtue being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes concomitant, their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours taking notice of their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, began to be jealous, and by degrees, reſolv'd to oppoſe them. However they thought it not fit abruptly to declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves their enemies, but by a neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and more cleanly piece of ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110049:8"/>they concluded to interrupt them privately in their commerce, and by that means to force them at laſt to begin the rupture them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. If our new Planters, in the poſture they were in at that time, were defective in any thing, it was in their conduct and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of War, which muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged was not ſo exact, as their rudiments for Peace. But theſe great perſons having but one ſoul (as it were) and acting by one motion, in a ſhort time eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht ſuch <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Maximes</hi> for War, that they were own'd the principal Souldiers of that Age, and have been ever ſince eſteem'd not only the ableſt Politicians, but the moſt potent enemies in the World.</p>
            <p>This being the Cradle or Mould in which this great body was form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and continued till it grew
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110049:8"/>ſtronger and adult, it has ſince not only ventur'd abroad amongſt its Neighbours, but acquainted it ſelf with the moſt remote corners of the Univerſe, for what Countrey is it which has not taſted of her commerce, or what part is there of the Levant Seas that is not afraid of her Arms, in ſpight of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the <hi>Turk.</hi> It will not be amiſs if I follow their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in my deſcription of their Civil, and Military Policy, the firſt being the baſis and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of their grandure, and the laſt that which has advanc't them to a miraculous height, and render'd them formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all over the World. I ſhall begin with their Civil Affairs, and when I have made relation of what I obſerv'd (in my Travels) of that kind, I ſhall proceed to their Militia,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110049:9"/>in which having ſerv'd alſo for ſome time, I made my Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations according to my Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:110049:9"/>
            <head>THE POLICY OF THE <hi>VENETIAN,</hi> Both Civil and Military.</head>
            <div n="1" type="book">
               <head>The Firſt Book. <hi>Their Civil Policy.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Duke.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat a body without a head how vigorous and robuſt ſoever it may be, is notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding but an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable Trunck, and inanimate Maſs, is ſo clear,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110049:10"/>and inexpugnable a truth, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but alleadg'd in a Fable to the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> when in defiance of the tyranny of the Senate they were retired into the Mount <hi>Aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tini,</hi> it brought the numerous and unquiet multitude down again to their obedience, and wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to ſubmit to a domination they believ'd before inſupportable. Accordingly the Republick of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> underſtanding of what impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance it would be, never thought themſelves ſafe or compleat, till they had made themſelves a Chief.</p>
                  <p>And this Election as I conceive was grounded upon three principal Reaſons: The firſt was to fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the hopes of the ambitious, who would not ſo readily embrace any deſign againſt their Countrey, nor attempt the ſubverſion of their liberties, ſeeing a Prince already
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110049:10"/>in poſſeſſion of the place, (by the univerſal conſent of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth) which he might other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deſire to uſurp. The ſecond, to cool and aſſwage that heat of dominion which reigns in the breaſt of moſt of the Gentry, by giving every man hopes of arriving one day at the Supremacy, it being moſt certain, there is not one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the Nobles but has his expectation, and ſometime or other may pretend to it. The third is to ſatisfie and fix the vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til ſpirit of the Commons, giving them an appearance of liberty in their Republick, and in their Dukes the ſhadow of a King.</p>
                  <p>I call it the ſhadow of a King, becauſe in reality the Prince which they chooſe has more of the Name than Authority, and is ſo ſtrictly limited and circumſcrib'd, that in an hours time the Grand Councel
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110049:11"/>(which they call the Councel of ten) can call him to account, form a Proceſs againſt him, and caſhier him. He is I muſt needs ſay accommodated well enough, and magnificently lodg'd, yet he is but as it were an illuſtrious Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, ſeldom permitted to go out of his Pallace, and when he does, it is <hi>incognito,</hi> without any Enſigns of his place. That which is moſt ſtrange, is, to oblige him to keep cloſe and at home, if the people have taken any diſguſt againſt their <hi>Doge</hi> or Duke, they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to throw ſtones at him, and to commit what inſolencies they pleaſe, if they meet him in the Streets, or in his <hi>Gondolo,</hi> except it be upon Feſtivals or publick Ceremonies, when he is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by the Senate, and all the Ambaſſadors in the Town.</p>
                  <p>Being the moſt jealous people in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110049:11"/>the World of their liberties, they could not find a better expedient than that, to keep their Prince low and dependant, and to cut off all wayes he might poſſibly take to make himſelf abſolute. For not being allowed to do any thing of himſelf, it cannot be apprehended he can attempt or accompliſh any thing of importance, beſides the very Officers and Servants of his Houſhold, are recommended and paid by the Commonwealth, and by conſequence expecting nothing from him but the honour of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, they are not ſo weak, to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the preferment they may rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally hope for, by being faithfull to thoſe which plac't them in that Sphear.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs in ſome things he has the reverence or reſemblance of a Prince, he has admiſſion into all publick Counſels, he has a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110049:12"/>double voice in reſpect of his qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, he has precedence of all the Nobility, and the whole Senate, he creates all Officers, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes all Offices, he gives out Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and makes moſt part (though not all) of the Ordinances, yet all this is with ſo much dependance, that he may be ſaid to do nothing alone without the aſſiſtance of the ſaid Number, ſome of which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of attending him in point of honour, are as ſo many Spies watching over his actions perpetually. They chooſe their Dukes commonly the moſt ancient that they can, as well to ſatisfie many in a ſhort time, as believing the ardour of dominion to be dead and extinguiſh't, in perſons of their age.</p>
                  <p>In the four years time which I ſpent in their ſervice, I was a ſpectator of the Reigns and Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110049:12"/>of <hi>Contarini, Valiero,</hi> and <hi>Pezaro.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Ceremony in which the <hi>Doge</hi> appears in the greateſt ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and Majeſty is at the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> upon which day he marries the Sea with a Ring. At that time he makes a publick Feaſt; to which (in great State) he comes in very late, and makes but little ſtay, after which he marches in a moſt triumphant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion from the place where he lands, to the Church of St. <hi>Mark.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Take him in his <hi>Gondolo,</hi> (which is call'd <hi>le Bucentaure</hi>) and he is a Prince indeed, it is guilt all over to the very water, cover'd from the Poup to the Stroud with a large <hi>Baldaquin</hi> or Cloth of State, of Crimſon Velvet embroider'd with gold and ſilver, with a rich Fringe of the ſame: he is ſet upon a kind
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110049:13"/>of a little Throne, the Senate ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on both ſides of him, bare: he is in a purple Veſt with a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem upon his head, which is a Bonnet of an odd kind of faſhion, encompaſt with a <hi>Band Royal</hi> of white <hi>a l'antique,</hi> a habit which nevertheleſs has ſomething Auguſt and Majeſtick in it. In this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, at no great expence they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their Prince to reign for one day; yet 'tis remarkeable alſo that even in the midſt of this Grandure, they give him a gentle remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his dependance, and the hazard he will run if he exceeds the bounds they have preſcrib'd, and that is by conducting him betwixt two pillars, which is to be the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal place of his chaſtiſement, if he attempts any thing againſt their liberties.</p>
                  <p>Could any body with greater addreſs reſtrain the imperious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110049:13"/>of thoſe, who tranſported with the Grandure of their dignity, are not contented with the ſtation and mediocrity in which the Rules of the Republick have plac't them? Could any more gently and more agreeably lull that furious paſſion aſleep, which not only diſturbs, but ſubverts ſo many States?</p>
                  <p>But the excellency of their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks conſiſts in the Election of their Dukes, it being a fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and inviolable Law amongſt them, That no perſon how quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſoever in reſpect of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, can be admitted to that dignity if he be married, and if all their Chronicles be conſulted from the very foundation of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth to this day, there will not be above two or three to be found who have had Wives. For knowing very well the ambition of that Sex, and their inſatiate appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110049:14"/>to govern, they have excluded them by a Law which allows them no preheminence though their Husbands be Princes. Knowing likewiſe how violent the paſſion of that Countrey is towards them, and how inclinable even to the moſt ſervile reſpects, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that a man though otherwiſe very honeſt and devoted to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of his Countrey, may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding be too weak to defend himſelf againſt the importunities of his Wife, and it being contrary to the Laws both Humane and Divine to ſeparate thoſe who they have mutually joyn'd, by a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar dexterity they have avoided both the one inconvenience, and the other, and decreed no perſon capable of Election but ſuch as are ſingle, whereby it proceeds that neither their Sons, nor Relations, are the more conſiderable amongſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110049:14"/>them, nor live in any greater ſplendor than before, not being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the leaſt priviledge to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their alliance to the Prince. Nay ſo far is it from that, the Duke is not permitted to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe privately with any of them unleſs ſome body be by, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that as ſoon as he is choſen to that dignity, he bids adieu to his Children, his Friends, his Family, and all that is dear to him, none of them being ſuffer'd to enter into the Palace with him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:110049:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Counſel of Ten.</head>
                  <p>TO ſpeak properly, the Counſel of Ten are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoul of that Liberty which the <hi>Venetians</hi> have preſerv'd immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late for twelve hundred years. They are the Poles upon which that potent Machine moves, in which the perpetual and inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible courſe of their Wiſdom is to be admir'd. They are the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains from whence thoſe Maximes have ſprung, which rightly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, have hitherto ſucceeded, and advanc't their reputation to the condition it is in. In ſhort, though the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110049:15"/>them in number, they came ſhort of that refulgent puiſſance and addreſs which imbelliſhes this little body.</p>
                  <p>They are choſen above-board, without any favour or under-hand dealing, for the moſt part perſons experienc't in publick affairs from their very youth, and in truth ſuch as are elected into this Soveraign Counſel, are ordinarily well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc't in years, it being but neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary a State of that importance ſhould be entruſted to no hands, but ſuch as have been accuſtomed to the greateſt Negotiations. They are more Soveraign, than their Soveraign himſelf, for (as hath been ſaid before) if the ſafety and advantage of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth requires it, they can pull him down, and degrade him as they pleaſe.</p>
                  <p>They have ſecret and unconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110049:16"/>wayes of diſcovering what is done in the State, beſides their private, they have publick infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations which give them very conſiderable advice. They have one <hi>Denoncie</hi> (as they call them) particularly for Oaths, which is a thing cannot be forbidden too ſtrictly. They have others for pompous extravagancies in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, and it is no more than is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in ſo opulent a State, where the Youth and Nobility are as it were glutted with riches, and doubtleſs was there not a ſevere hand kept over them, we ſhould ſee their Veſts and their black Bonnets in a ſhort time upon the ground, and their <hi>Damoiſelles</hi> clat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in their gold and their ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, with as much profuſion and vanity as they do with us.</p>
                  <p>This Law againſt extravagance in their Cloathes, is ſo rigid and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110049:16"/>auſtere, that the Curtezans them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, who in other things have great priviledges, are not exempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this. And one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt paenal charges can be brought againſt them, is to accuſe them of having their Gowns or their Cloathes too rich, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the preſcription of that Edict. By this Policy it is, the mediocrity (which was the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal aim of their Anceſtors) is maintain'd to this day. This it is which prevents the tranſportation of their Money into forreign parts, and hinders the luxury of that Sex which moſt commonly occaſions it.</p>
                  <p>They have another <hi>Denoncie</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the affairs of State, and this is the moſt dreadfull and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous of them all: for a perſon inform'd againſt by a Billett or Ticket thrown privately into the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110049:17"/>mouth of this <hi>Denoncie,</hi> is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately apprehended, and clapt up cloſe in a horrible Dungeon, where he lyes without any poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of knowing the cauſe of his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, till after ſome time he be confronted at a little Window by the perſon which accus'd him, where he may apologize if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but being ſeldom believ'd, (ſuch is their extraordinary jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of their freedom) they are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently condemn'd to the Canal call'd <hi>Orphano,</hi> which is the place of Execution, where (let his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be what it will) they faſten him to a board, and tying Cannon Bullets to his feet, and others to his head, they let him down bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>xt two Boats into the Water.</p>
                  <p>That which I call <hi>Denoncies</hi> are certain Mouthes cut with a Chiffel on the outſide of the Walls of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110049:17"/>Palace, which correſpond to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ain Pipes falling into Boxes of Stone within of which the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ors of the Counſel of Ten keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Keyes, and thoſe that are in ſervice do viſit them every night, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ſee what fatal information is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that day.</p>
                  <p>It was the deſign of the grave Politicians which eſtabliſh'd this Counſel, to advance their number <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Ten, to prevent combination <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r partiality in their affairs, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng almoſt impoſſible in ſo many, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut one or other will prefer the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ereſt of the Commonwealth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore his own, and becauſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot keep our ſelves from certain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hwartings and accerſſions to ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eople as we have alwayes in our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye, the Senate did very wiſely comply with the courſe of our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane affections, and encreaſe them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o that number, to divide and bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110049:18"/>their ſentiments, if not by a generous inclination to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, at leaſt by an inſuperable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of Nature, which ſuffers us not to concur with the judgement of every one.</p>
                  <p>This Counſel or Magiſtrate (for that is the name they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly call it by) is the ſame which is call'd in <hi>France</hi> the Privy Counſel of State, in which the Prince himſelf does ſometimes preſide. But there is this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them, in <hi>France</hi> all things are tranſacted according to the pleaſure of the King, and if he cannot be preſent amongſt them himſelf, he ſubſtitutes another, and he is call'd Preſident of the Counſel, but the <hi>Doge</hi> is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes admitted to their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies himſelf, and ſo far from depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting another, that they will no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vouchſafe to communicate their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110049:18"/>tranſactions with him, but now and then. This Counſel is the Eye that watches perpetually for the good and ſafety of the State, the Eye which never fleeps, which divides their care and ſollicitude for their Countrey with ſo much equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and proportion, that let one come to the Palace when he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, he ſhall alwayes find them rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to diſpatch them, foraſmuch as there is not an hour in the night but they ſucceed and relieve one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in order, that they may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ready to act, and oppoſe themſelves againſt all the machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their enemies.</p>
                  <p>This is the Court of the higheſt Juriſdiction, which judges and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines abſolutely without appeal in all things, eſpecially belonging to the Publick. They have the Authority of chaſtizing the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which they can extend very
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110049:19"/>far if they think good. The Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals receive all their Orders from them, and when their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are expir'd, they are oblig'd within ſix moneths next enſuing to attend that Court, and to anſwer to ſuch Queſtions as ſhall be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, in caſe they be accus'd of abuſing their Commands. But whether there be any information againſt them or not, it is their duty of courſe to preſent themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them to give them an account of their Moneys, Magazines, Men, and whatever elſe was under their Conduct and Authority.</p>
                  <p>The great Power which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe makes them not only venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but dreadfull, and their Prince himſelf not daring to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict their Decrees, they have gotten ſuch an Empire upon the ſpirits of all people, that the very name of the Counſel of Ten will
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:110049:19"/>make one tremble, though his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence be never ſo ſmall. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments with us, and even our Counſels of State, have not that force and authority as they: in all our tranſactions, their motions are but ſlow, their power bounded, and reſtrain'd, which hinders their diſpatch, and certainly could they exerciſe their zeal with the ſame priviledge and freedom as theſe, there would not be ſo many muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and conſpiracies in <hi>France,</hi> nor ſo many cruel Wars to deſtroy us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:110049:20"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Sages Grands.</head>
                  <p>THey are alwayes Elected out of the Nobility, nor can a meer Citizen ever hope to arrive at that honour. They are choſen for their merit and capacity, and their places are never ſold. In ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects they are like our Secretaries of State. They are three princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal perſons which have a kind of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-intendancy over the reſt, and manage the ſprings and motions of that great Machine the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. They have each of them their peculiar Province which they adminiſter diſtinctly, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is the <hi>Sage de la Mer,</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:110049:20"/>the <hi>Sage de la Terre-ferme,</hi> and the <hi>Sage de l' Ecriture.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Sage de la Mer</hi> diſpoſes of all Orders which are given, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any wayes to Maritime affairs, there being nothing happens in that nature which paſſes not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his hands. He has the care and proviſion of all Arms, Victuals, and Ammunitions, and gives out all Commiſſions requiſite thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. He gives Patents and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to all the Commanders and Officers in their Galleys and Gallions. He Signs all neceſſary Orders, and conveys them to them, and in ſhort has full cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance and authority over all their Navigation.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Sage de la terre-ferme</hi> has the ſame inſpection upon the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, takes an accompt of all Chamberlains, and Treaſures of the Armies. It is his office to pay
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110049:21"/>the Souldiers, to give all Orders to the Militia in Garriſon in all places under his dominion, and in a word it is he is to be apply'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, in any thing relating to affairs upon land.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Sage de l' Ecriture</hi> has the overſight of the Records and Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Counſel, Signs all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which paſs there, ſees the Letters Patents and Commiſſions ſeal'd which are given to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſent abroad to govern and command the Provinces, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is receiv'd from the Senate, either recompence, donative, or office, but muſt paſs through his hands. Each of theſe Grandees are allow'd their Secretaries and Clarks under them for their aſſiſtance, and they are Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens.</p>
                  <p>The mark or enſign of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree is a long purple Robe with large Sleeves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:110049:21"/>They have ſeparated theſe Offices, and made them three, though in moſt Kingdoms they are commonly executed by one perſon, but their deſign was to enfeeble and debilitate all dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, which in one mans hand might be too puiſſant and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. They have each of them a Seal belonging parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to their Office, with which they ſeal their ſeveral diſpatches, but all of them have the ſame impreſſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:110049:22"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of their Procurators.</head>
                  <p>THe Procurators in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick may be called Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces without a Soleciſm, and they are of two ſorts: One is choſen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes by the Senate, and confer'd as a reward of ſome emiment piece of ſervice, or elſe as an encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of virtue and honeſty. The other buy their Principalities, and for the moſt part very dear, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the readieſt wayes the Commonwealth takes to raiſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in their greateſt and moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant neceſſities.</p>
                  <p>They have their places in all Counſels, and <hi>Pregadis,</hi> but they have but a ſingle voice no more
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110049:22"/>than the privateſt Gentleman, and can do no more than any of the reſt; yet they have their perquiſites and priviledges, which makes them many times very conſiderable, and enables them to oblige or gratifie any one for whom they have a kindneſs.</p>
                  <p>All Nations which have any commerce with the <hi>Venetian,</hi> are very ſollicitous to acquire one of theſe Procurators for their Patrons. The Towns upon the <hi>terra-ferma,</hi> put themſelves under their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tections, and even the Nobility themſelves think it no ſmall corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boration to have an alliance with one of theſe Princes; and this is that which gives the greateſt luſtre to that Office.</p>
                  <p>In the Senate they have their places above the reſt, have the preheminence in all debates, and are alwayes the firſt in giving their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110049:23"/>judgements. Yet for all theſe prerogatives, their train is no greater than theirs, nor are they ſuffer'd to walk the Streets in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Equipage, and the deſign is to keep that happy mediocrity invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, which was eſtabliſh't at the Commencement, and has been continued ſo fortunately ever ſince. Nevertheleſs in their Houſes they appear like themſelves, living with the greateſt affluence and gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure imaginable. Strangers are not admitted to ſpeak with them till they have formally demanded audience firſt; and when it is granted them, they are conducted by a long train of Officers of his Chamber to the place where they are to be receiv'd. Moſt of them are very proud and moroſe, but ſome of them civil and fine Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: In the time whilſt I was in their ſervice, one of theſe Princes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110049:23"/>named <hi>Moroſini</hi> managed his digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo nobly, he gain'd the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all people, and put them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an equal admiration of the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his behaviour, the noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his extraction, and the charms with which he attracted the hearts of all ſuch as had occaſion to approach him; a virtue (to ſpeak truth) with which the <hi>Venetian</hi> Nobility have but little acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
                  <p>They are diſtinguiſh't from the reſt by a Magiſtrale Robe, of the ſame colour with the Robe of the <hi>Sages Grands.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:110049:24"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of their Podeſtats.</head>
                  <p>THe Dignities of the <hi>Podeſtats</hi> are of no long duration, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing not above two or three years in the Towns to which they are ſent for the diſtribution of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. Their Office is properly to hear and diſpatch all Suits or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies ariſing either in the Towns where they preſide, or the Territories depending.</p>
                  <p>From the day of their departure from <hi>Venice,</hi> and their entrance upon the Magiſtracy, they lay by the equality in which they lived before, and comport themſelves as Soveraigns. They have their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110049:24"/>Gentlemen, their Stewards, their Officers of their Chambers, their Confeſſors, their Pages, their Footmen, and their Guard, which conſiſts commonly of thirty or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty perſons, with a peculiar ſort of Bonnetts upon their heads, their Swords by their ſides, and their Snap-hanches in their hands after the manner of the <hi>Breſſians,</hi> which is a kind of Arquebuſs, ſomewhat larger than our Muſquetons. The Guards are alwayes drawn up, and in their Arms, at the Gate of the Court where the <hi>Podeſtats</hi> hold their Aſſizes, and attend him conſtantly whenever he goes abroad.</p>
                  <p>Though the Senate allow their <hi>Podeſtats</hi> theſe priviledges, yet they will not ſuffer them in other things to behave themſelves like Princes, leſt the elation of their heart might make them forget their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110049:25"/>ſtation and dependance. Their Juriſdiction ſeldom extending above four or five leagues, they cannot have <hi>intereſt</hi> or power enough to attempt any innovation; yet what authority they have given them, is to imprint a character of reſpect and obedience in the people under their ſeveral juriſdictions, that the Majeſty of theſe Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents may as a <hi>Copy</hi> repreſent the original Grandure of that auguſt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, of which theſe are as it were, the moſt inconſiderable mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
                  <p>Their Robes and their habits are red, their Veſt is of ſcarlet with large Sleeves, they are daily at Maſs in their Chappels, with the uſual Ceremonies, and thoſe of their Counſel accompanying them. Their Counſels conſiſt generally of Gentlemen of the <hi>Terra-ferma,</hi> who ſeem to be aſſiſtant and joyn'd
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110049:25"/>to theſe <hi>Podeſtats,</hi> in the diſcuſſion of all occurrences which preſent themſelves, but indeed it is but a complement and ſhadow of liberty which they give them, for in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of greateſt importance they never are called; and if by accident they be there, and their judgement contrary to the <hi>Podeſtats,</hi> they ſtop their mouthes, by ſhewing them a Decree of the Senate, confirm'd by the opinion of the preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
                  <p>They have authority over all Priſoners, and judge in all Caſes of life and death, in the higheſt <hi>reſort.</hi> They have the care of all Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, High-wayes, and Bridges. During the time of their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they lay Tolls, and ſet prices upon all things brought into the Markets, as neceſſary for the life of man. The Innes and victualling Houſes are oblig'd every night to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:110049:26"/>bring to them the names of all the Gueſts and Lodgers in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Houſes, by which means they underſtand not only the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, but the qualities of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which come into their Towns. If they have any apprehenſion of the Plague, they chooſe another Officer under them which is call'd the <hi>Magiſtrate of Health,</hi> who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers no man to enter whatever he be without a Ticket or atteſtation ſigned by their Secretaries. No Nobleman (I mean of the <hi>Terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferma</hi>) is allow'd to be abſent, but by their permiſſion; and ſo ſtrict is their eye over all numerous Aſſemblies, there is ſeldom any ſufficient to give them an alarm. They live after the manner of the Gentlemen of that Countrey, yet though they converſe with them freely, and afford them familiar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, it is alwayes with ſuch cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:110049:26"/>as make them know them to be their Maſters.</p>
                  <p>To inſinuate however into the affection of the Gentry, and oblige them in ſome meaſure, they vouchſafe them ſome little incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable imployment, where they have the entire management of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and yet they call this, (as I have heard ſome of them my ſelf) ſharing their authority with them, and deſiring earneſtly their aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, when (in truth) they are but their ſervants, and led about by the Noſes, as they are pleas'd to direct.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:110049:27"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of their Camerlingues.</head>
                  <p>I Might adde in this place an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer they call the <hi>Captain Grand,</hi> but his imployment being Military, I ſhall reſerve him till I ſpeak of their Militia, and paſs to their <hi>Camerlingues,</hi> or Receivers, which for the moſt part are <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Gentlemen of ſmall Eſtates, who are put into thoſe Offices on purpoſe to recruit themſelves, which they ſeldom neglect, by the ſeveral Receipts and payments which they make; and the Senate has that kindneſs for them, they never enquire too ſtrictly into their behaviour. They are habit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:110049:27"/>in ſcarlet like the <hi>Podeſtat,</hi> receive their Orders both from the <hi>Podeſtat,</hi> and <hi>Grand-Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and diſcharge their Bills. When they hold a fair cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency with theſe two Magiſtrates, they make up their Markets the better, and they are continued in this little (but advantageous) Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, till ſuch time as they are ſuppos'd to have got e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to ſupport their qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the Commonwealth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:110049:28"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of their Ambaſſadors.</head>
                  <p>THe principal aim of their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy is to obtain and preſerve an amity with all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> by all poſſible means, of which they are ſo great lovers, they have many times purcha'ſt it at a dear rate, of the cruelleſt of their enemies. One of the moſt powerfull and dexterous wayes of maintaining this union with forreign Kingdoms, is by this ancient mode of Ambaſſadors, which they ſend to all Courts in Chriſtendom with great equipage and ſplendor. They chooſe them conſtantly out of the <hi>Patrician</hi> race, that is to ſay
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:110049:28"/>of the ancient Senators, ſuch as were the firſt of their State, and ſuch if poſſible as have merit and abilities added to the Nobility of their bloud.</p>
                  <p>They are permitted to habit themſelves according to the faſhion of the Countrey to which they are deſigned, and to live after another manner than they do at <hi>Venice,</hi> which ſcarce one of the other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates dare venture to do.</p>
                  <p>In theſe kind of Negotiations they are ſo ſubtil and accute, they can penetrate the moſt ſecret Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binets of Kings, and by a Key of gold which is forg'd in the Senate, open and ſhut the moſt obſcure and intricate Springs in any ſoveraign Counſel. They ſpare no charges upon ſuch an occaſion, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where they have any ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Ambaſſador <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſeem
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:110049:29"/>Plenipotentiaries, and to have a full power and authority, but they are really circumſcrib'd. They dare not come to a definitive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion upon any affair whatever, till they have given notice of their progreſs at <hi>Venice,</hi> and receiv'd the directions of the Senate, which is punctually to be obſerv'd. They have not the liberty to open and peruſe any Packets or diſpatches alone: to prevent that, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point them certain Citizens of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> ſelected out of the moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and experienc't perſons of the City, who as Secretaries are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be preſent at the opening and reading of their Letters.</p>
                  <p>And this is no ſmall check to the Nobility, for however glorious they may appear in their ſtation, we ſee them liable to be curb'd, and that by one ſingle Citizen. With ſuch admirable prudence do
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110049:29"/>theſe great Stateſmen confine all their Grandees to their particular circuits and bounds, that 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for them to arrogate any abſolute juriſdiction to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p>The reports which theſe Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries make, either by their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or word of mouth, are of ſo great credit with the Senate, that they are not only ſufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy a man, but to create a jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and interrupt that harmony and conſort which might otherwiſe be found amongſt perſons of the ſame condition. The Republick names a Nobleman expreſly, to whom it gives the appearance of being chief of the Embaſſie, but when that is done, he is ſure to have a Citizen clap't at his Elbow, to peep into the moſt ſecret of his actions. It is an incredible thing to ſee with what generoſity theſe
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110049:30"/>illuſtrious perſons the next day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they are return'd from their Embaſſies, lay aſide all the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and Glory which they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon them for the honour of their Conntrey, and march up and down the Streets as it were <hi>incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nito,</hi> with the ſame modeſty as an ordinary Citizen. This condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion of theirs gains ſtrangely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the affections of their Subjects and diſpoſes them to obedience without violence or coerſion, for obſerving how quietly their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours reſign, they cannot think much to conform to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment themſelves.</p>
                  <p>As to the Ambaſſadors which are ſent to <hi>Venice,</hi> they are receiv'd with great honours. The Senate in their Robes of ſcarlet go out in their <hi>Gondoloes</hi> to meet them, in ſome of the Iſles about the Town and having made their Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110049:30"/>they conduct them to the City with a great train of Boats at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, every Senator taking a Gentleman of the Ambaſſadors Equipage into his <hi>Gondolo</hi> with him.</p>
                  <p>But after this day they have no liberty to ſee or converſe together more, nor can the Ambaſſador himſelf ſpeak or negotiate with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny of them upon any pretence whatſoever. All things after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards are tranſacted in full Senate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Duke and Counſel being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent, where no immediate Anſwer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ever given to any Propoſition, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut the Ambaſſadors withdrawing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he buſineſs is debated, and then put to the Vote what ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd.</p>
                  <p>The Laws are ſo jealous, and ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>evere in matters of Intelligence or Correſpondence, that if it be known a noble <hi>Venetian</hi> has had
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110049:31"/>conference, not only with an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, but the leaſt perſon in his Retinue, he runs no leſs hazard than of his life, inſomuch that they run as faſt and with as much horror from any of them, as from a Baſilisk. About twenty ſix years ſince, one of the Family of the <hi>Contarini,</hi> and Nephew to the <hi>Doge</hi> that was then, was ſtrangled in Priſon for having been ſeen in a <hi>Gondoloe</hi> with a Secretary of <hi>Spain.</hi> A Friend of mine, one <hi>Labia</hi> a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Venetian,</hi> who had ſpent much of his time in <hi>France,</hi> when <hi>Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur du Pleſſis Beſancon</hi> took his leave of the Senate, admiring the beauty and accompliſhment of the young <hi>Chevalier</hi> his Son, he could not contain himſelf from ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſting him, and paying his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, but ſuſpecting that one of the Counſel of Ten (who are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes about the Ambaſſadors)
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:110049:31"/>had obſerv'd him, he was glad of his own accord to throw himſelf at the feet of thoſe terrible Judges, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his fault, and implore their pardon, which at length though with ſevere reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he obtain'd, becauſe he had prevented their Inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by accuſing himſelf.</p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:110049:32"/>
                  <p>chooſe their <hi>Doge,</hi> their Counſel of Ten, their Senators, their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, their <hi>Sages Grands,</hi> their <hi>Podeſtats,</hi> their Captains-General, their Provediteurs-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, their Governours, their Grand-Captains, their Vice-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirals of their Galleys, the heads of their Inquiſition, (which is but the ſhadow of a Court in <hi>Venice</hi>) becauſe let the Inquiſitors be as zealous as they will, they can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther act nor undertake any thing, without the permiſſion of certain Senators appointed to aſſiſt, who commonly (like the reſt of the Nation) being not over-ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous or ſevere in ſuch matters, do choak and correct the ardour which your more refin'd Catholicks are prone to. In ſhort, all the chief Offices depending upon the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, (whether Military or Civil) are entruſted only with the noble
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:110049:32"/>
                     <hi>Venetians,</hi> the reſt of the Citizens, and the nobleſt upon the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, never ſo much as hoping for them in their turns.</p>
                  <p>Till they be five and twenty years old, the noble <hi>Venetians</hi> are not admitted into the Counſel, yet this ſeverity is not ſo general, but ſome few which are of their friends are receiv'd at twenty. Here it is they model and form their young plants for the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the State; here it is they are inſtructed in their moſt refin'd policies, and prepared for publick affairs. And though it may ſeem ſtrange that the heat of youth ſhould accord with the coldneſs and aſperity of old age, yet there has been alwayes obſerv'd ſo great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n union and concurrence reſulting from their Counſels, that it muſt be acknowledg'd the flame of the young Gentlemen has hitherto had
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:110049:33"/>no other effect but to correct and qualifie the frigidity of the more ancient, and on the other ſide the Ice and gravity of the ſeniors have ſerv'd only to cool and temper the juvenile ebullitions of their juniors.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Pregadis</hi> (which are the Counſels to which they are uſually called, as is imply'd by the name, for <hi>Pregadi</hi> in the <hi>Venetiau</hi> language is as much as invited or convok'd) have their firſt meeting (all in a body) in the <hi>Place of St. Mark,</hi> where every one driving on his own deſigns either for himſelf or ſuch of his friends as are ambitious of authority, they walk up and down promiſcuouſly, ſolliciting, and making their Cabals.</p>
                  <p>No body is ſuffer'd at that time to come near the place where they are walking, and if by accident or preſumption any ſtranger intrudes
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110049:33"/>himſelf, he is repuls'd, and runs a great hazard of ſome publick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front. The while they are there, the place is counted as ſacred, and call'd by the name of <hi>Pregadi,</hi> it runs along all the front of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and takes up a full half of the Market-place in breadth. One cuſtome they have, I know not whether more ſubtil or pleaſant: When any one who has ſtood for any dignity, comes out of the Counſel, whether his ambition be proſperous or not, all people ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute him with their Complements, congratulate his advancement, and by a peculiar Oath which they have on purpoſe, ſwear they have done their utmoſt to ſerve him, by which means the poor rejected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, beſides the affront he receiv'd being defeated of his hopes, finds himſelf under a neceſſity of receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a civility from him, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:110049:34"/>was the principal deſtruction of his deſigns, for he can never be aſſured, who were either his friends or his foes, becauſe the Elections being made by Tickets put into a Baſon without any ſuperſcription, the whole conduct remains ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd and obſcure, it would be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the skill of an <hi>Oedipus</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve him.</p>
                  <p>This invention of Tickets is the moſt ſafe way was ever found out for giving their judgements freely, for who is it will deny, but when one is to give his opinion in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Aſſembly, he is not liable to certain inſuperable motions, which oblige him many times to ſpeak againſt his judgement, being to give his Vote againſt ſome great perſon which he is afraid to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe, or againſt a Friend which he is unwilling to deſtroy, againſt a man of parts which perchance he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110049:34"/>has occaſion to uſe, or againſt a man of power that another time may do as much for him. But this occult way of Election defends them againſt thoſe dangers, and authoriſeth them to be honeſt, without apprehenſion of any body.</p>
                  <p>If there be ſeveral Children in a Family, the elder ſeldom marry, but give a good proportion of their patrimony to the younger: it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that the youngeſt marryes for them all; but I cannot think them extravagant to that point. This I know, they are in no great ſlavery to their conſciences, they manage their appetites with a looſe rein, and indulge themſelves in their pleaſures as much as any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the world, yet they have a jealous and ſuſpicious humour, (which is born and dyes with them) that perſwades me the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:110049:35"/>good man of the houſe would not digeſt that kind of community. In my judgement it proceeds ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from a Maxime of State if one only marryes, for the whole Eſtate devolving by degrees upon him, he has wherewithall not only to ſupport his Family, but to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it in its opulence and ſplendor, which they are principally ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous of, not enduring with any pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to ſee any exceed them, and by this means (I conceive) it is they preſerve their Houſes in their ancient authority and luſture.</p>
                  <p>Under their black Veſts they are habited in the <hi>French</hi> faſhion, very handſome, the young Nobility having no fancy for the long Robes which they are oblig'd to wear, would willingly change them alſo, but in that they are oblig'd to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate, and preſerve the mode of their Countrey, which in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:110049:35"/>all great Towns, and in their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of pleaſure, they retain to their dying day. But out of the Towns, they are dreſs'd <hi>a la Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liere,</hi> either when they are in their Coaches, or on Horſeback, and accompani'd by a rabble of Hectors they call <hi>Bravi,</hi> many times only in oſtentation, but too often for a worſe end, for being very proud and vindicative, they are ſeldom without ſome miſchief or other in their deſigns. And for that in this Countrey courage does not lye in the gallantry or generouſneſs of a mans behaviour, but in ridding himſelf of his enemy by what wayes he can. That they may be in no danger of being ſurprized themſelves, but rather have that advantage upon others, they are attended when they are in the Countrey with theſe <hi>Mirmidons,</hi> but in the City they leave them in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110049:36"/>garriſon, ſometimes in their Houſes, but never appear with them in the Streets.</p>
                  <p>They never diſcourage their youth in their debauches, they ſeem rather to excite them by the permiſſion the <hi>Curtezans</hi> have to keep publick Houſes without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſturb'd, though to do them right it is in a Quarter by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They are not ignorant in the Senate, that a voluptuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thinks of nothing but his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and he which is inveigled by the artifice of a <hi>Curtezan,</hi> purſues no bodies deſtruction but his own, and aims no further than to make himſelf acceptable to her. By this means theſe grave Senators ſuffer the inextinguiſhable flames of their youth, to evaporate betwixt the arms of theſe Idols, and with this ſweet poiſon correct the boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe ſpirits, which unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jol'd
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:110049:36"/>might endanger, at leaſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the ſubverſion of the State. But ſince the famous <hi>Tiepolo</hi>'s dayes, there has not been known any form'd Conſpiracy ſufficient to give that Republick any apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; what have happen'd, have been immediately ſuppreſs'd, and by their vigilance render'd abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
                  <p>They are generally much given to play, and very neat and ſubtil at all Games. They have certain places on purpoſe which they call <hi>Redotti,</hi> where they meet, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of ſeveral hours without ſpeaking a word. Their ſucceſs is never known by their behaviour, for they win and loſe, receive and part with their money with the ſame temper and indifference. For the moſt part the place of their play is at a Senators Houſe, where they have alwayes one of their
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:110049:37"/>Judges in their eye. They are ſo far from uſing any corporal Exerciſe, that they deſpiſe it; and I am of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion they are brought up purpoſely in that lazineſs, leſt otherwiſe they ſhould awake their Lethargick ſpirits, which by this means lye buried in the contemplation and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their pleaſures.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:110049:37"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of their Ladies.</head>
                  <p>THe Ladies making no incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of the Nobleſs in this Countrey, I ſuppoſe it will be allow'd me to make a ſmall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in their behalf, and to ſpeak a word or two of their Cuſtomes <hi>en paſſant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They are naturally very proud, and of opinion there is no Nobility like themſelves in the whole world. They never match be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath themſelves, and will ſooner throw themſelves into a Nunnery, (where they have all fort of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) than entertain the leaſt moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an unequal Marriage. In
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110049:38"/>their Houſes they are very magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and rich, their Habits of Cloth of gold, or other coſtly Stuff, made up <hi>à la Françoiſe.</hi> When they appear abroad they are dreſs'd very neatly, their Breaſts bare, and commonly plump and white, their Heads are uſually dreſs'd after our mode, and with as much curioſity as in <hi>France.</hi> When Madam <hi>Beſançon</hi> was at <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> they moſt induſtriouſly imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her in all the faſhions ſhe brought with her out of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your languiſhing beauties being in no great requeſt among them, they prefer vivacity to ſweetneſs, and a brisk aiery brown is more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable there than a ſleepy and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſpect, though the faireſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable. They take much delight to have their Necks and Faces ſomething more ſanguine than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:110049:38"/>which to ſtrangers is not ſo gratefull. They are mightily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd at home, but if you will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with them there, they will invent wayes enough to ſatisfie your curioſity any where elſe. They have certain affected Feaſts every Week, upon which under pretence of publick prayer, or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular devotion to ſome Saint or other, they take occaſion to be conſtantly at Church, where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Pillars you may obſerve the young Gentlemen lying at catch for their <hi>Oeillades</hi> and Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which they receive and retort with a ſlyneſs and dexterity ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the cunning of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>They have moſt of them their Women abſurdly and fantaſtically clad, which attend and ſupport them, by whoſe gracious aſſiſtance a man may be ſometimes admitted
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110049:39"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:110049:39"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:110049:40"/>to converſe with them, when they enjoy themſelves moſt freely, or have liberty to walk. From the <hi>Epiphanie</hi> to the firſt Week in <hi>Lent</hi> they keep a continued <hi>Carnaval,</hi> during which time they have the freedom to go in their diſguiſes to the <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>St. Mark,</hi> to be preſent at all Balls, Playes or Aſſemblies, where there is merriment or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing. At their Maſques they have a particular care of refuſing their hand to no body, leſt it ſhould prove ſome Gentleman in <hi>Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade,</hi> which amongſt them would be an inexpiable affront. At theſe meetings they place themſelves all in a rowe, without ſpeaking a word, and when they are taken out to dance, one muſt have a ſpecial care he does it not with his Glove off, if he does, he not only runs a hazard of an affront, but to be piſtol'd or ſtabb'd. Their Dance
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:110049:40"/>is nothing but a grave and ſtately motion from one room to another, till at laſt they return to the place from whence they were taken. They have no want of Muſick, but it is ſo diſpoſed into ſeveral ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partments, that one is ſenſible but of one ſingle Melody. In one Chamber they have their Theor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boes, in another their Lutes, in a third their Viols, in a fourth their Violins, and ſo in every Chamber one comes, he is preſented with a new ſort.</p>
                  <p>Their Play is a perpetual <hi>Tacet.</hi> You ſhall ſee fifty or threeſcore La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies about a long Table, ſhuffling and managing the Cards with as much ſilence as they were Statues, and loſing their money with as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle concernment, as their Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands. I was many times at theſe meetings on purpoſe to have learn'd the game, but they play'd
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:110049:41"/>ſo quick, and talk'd ſo little, 'twas impoſſible I ſhould do it.</p>
                  <p>Beſides theſe Feaſts, they have the ſame liberty at the Marriage of any of their relations, upon certain dayes which they call <hi>Procuratici,</hi> and upon all publick ſolemnities for any victory obtain'd. When they are at home, their entertainment commonly is making their <hi>Punti in aria,</hi> which are the <hi>Points de Venice</hi> ſo much valu'd in <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Their Coaches are their <hi>Gondo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes,</hi> which are a ſort of Boats ſo eaſie and ſwift, it is ſcarce poſſible to preſent them to your imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. All the Summer long their recreation is upon the <hi>Canal</hi> above the <hi>Pontrealte,</hi> and they call this diverſion taking the Air. Their <hi>Gondoloes</hi> are ſo ſwift, though the Sea in the <hi>Canal</hi> be very gentle and calm, yet by the force of the Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the agitation of the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110049:41"/>it is ſwell'd and incens'd in that manner, it ſeems with its waves and foam to threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en all people that had the audacity to provoke it. But that which is moſt admirable is the dexterity of their Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termen, who amongſt ſo great a multitude and confuſion of Boats, ſo many turnings and windings as they make, are never known to fall foul up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one another, but follow ſo exactly the Barque where the Lady of their affections is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, that without the leaſt ſuſpicion or diſorder by all the croſſes they make, they will land you at the place where your Miſtriſs appoints.</p>
                  <p>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>here I might make ſome reflexion upon the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of this Nation, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire how upon certain occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:110049:42"/>they can maſter a paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which amongſt them is predominant. But they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the complexion of that Sex exactly, and that their deſire is more ardent of what is forbidden, for which reaſon they remit ſomething of the <hi>Italian</hi> ſeverity, and allow them a certain image of liberty, leſt by their ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they ſhould kindle ſuch a fire in their veins, as ſhould make their own Houſes too hot for them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:110049:42"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of their Citizens.</head>
                  <p>BEfore I come to ſpeak of the Eſtace upon the Continent, I think it not improper to place the Citizens next to the Nobility, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they pretend to be of the ſame number, and accordingly call themſelves Noble Citizens. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a man be very converſant amongſt them, and takes more than ordinary notice, it is no eaſie matter to diſtinguiſh them from the Gentry, they having the ſame habits, and neither of them more than the other; but if one aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates with them, and obſerves ſtrictly the difference of their geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110049:43"/>and ſpirit, 'tis not difficult to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them, for the Citizens carry not their heads ſo high, nor their forehead ſo open, their counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is not ſo free, they have more humility, and their ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are with more ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                  <p>They are generally men of parts, profound in their judgements, and have great intelligence in forreign Countreys. They are rich and frugal, and exerciſe no particular Trade, only they are Partners with ſuch as traffick in Groſs, their principal commerce is with the <hi>Jewes,</hi> who have a Quarter in the City aſſigned particularly to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. To ſpeak properly they are the chief of the Commons, and the Nobility complyes with them ſo far as to permit them to wear the ſame habits for three rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:110049:43"/>The firſt is, that by honouring them with the ſame Veſture the Senators themſelves wear, they may the better prevail with them to ſwallow their Authority, and cajole the Commons with an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that in their Citizens they do participate likewiſe with the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in the management of affairs, whereas indeed there is nothing common amongſt them but their Cloathes.</p>
                  <p>A ſecond is, to conceal the number of their Gentry from the obſervation of ſtrangers, that by ſuppoſing them more numerous than they are, they might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred from all plots and machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt them.</p>
                  <p>The laſt, and (if I be not miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) the moſt prevalent is, that by confounding themſelves in that manner with the commoner ſort, they might not remain ſo open and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:110049:44"/>eaſie a mark to ſuch as ſhould have deſigns againſt them, for he which attempts them upon preſumption of their habits, may find himſelf miſtaken, and involve himſelf in the ruine of a Citizen as ſoon as a Senator, ſo that their deſtruction by this means being not ſo facile as otherwiſe, theſe Citizens may be ſaid to be the Bucklers of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſs, by which they are cover'd and protected.</p>
                  <p>They are never imploy'd in any great Office, and have the management of nothing in the State, but under ſome of the Gentlemen of <hi>Venice.</hi> The higheſt of their preferment is to be Secretaries to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, Ambaſſadors, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veditors-General. They are admitted to the Bar, and may go as Voluntiers in any of the Ships belonging to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth;
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:110049:44"/>but that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are moſt pleas'd, and which perſwades them they have no ſmall ſhare in the Government, is, that they are nominated to their places by the Counſel, and indeed they are ſeldome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd about any perſon but as a ſpy upon his actions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:110049:45"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of the Nobles upon the <hi>Terra-firma.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>ONe of the moſt admirable things to all ſtrangers, is the ſubmiſſion (not to ſay abjectneſs and baſeneſs) of theſe Nobles to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Nobility of the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> which extends to ſo poor and ſervile a veneration, they will not put on their Hats before any of them, but by their reiterated com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. Notwithſtanding in the Countrey they retain ſome little eſteem, but in the City they are no more regarded than the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable Mechanicks.</p>
                  <p>They are kept in ſo conſtant and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:110049:45"/>ſo ſevere a ſervitude, they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver admitted to any conſiderable dignity in the Commonwealth. They are never call'd to any of the Counſels of State, of whoſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions they are uſually as ignorant as the meaneſt Fiſherman of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran.</hi> They are brought up in this ignorance, and kept at this diſtance from affairs, to keep them under, and prevent any competition with them who are to be their Maſters; for being naturally witty, quick; deſirous of novelties, and no more faithfull than conſiſts with their convenience, ſhould they give an inch, they would take an ell, and by the admiſſion of one foot, work in their whole body, till at laſt they would diſcover, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their maſque and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of liberty, they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and in effect no better than ſlaves. And to ſpeak truth, this
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:110049:46"/>Republick have ſo great a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and ſuſpicion of theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, there is no ſtone left unturn'd that may keep them from a fence of their condition, or put them out of any capacity of relieving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs that they might not provoke them to deſpair, the ſuperiour Magiſtrates, ſent over by the Senate to govern them, call them to them at their arrival, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt them (in appearance) with their affairs, give them the title of Counſellors, and perhaps the arbitration in ſome trifling diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
                  <p>The Orders which they receive from the Senate, they communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with them firſt, and they are oblig'd blindly to purſue them; they give them little Offices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, but they are not ſo honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as ſervile: with which ſhadows
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:110049:46"/>and deluſions the poor Gentlemen march off with an <hi>Adio à Voſigno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> as heartily as if they had ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd them to the higheſt dignity in their Dominions.</p>
                  <p>They are generally implacable, and hold this as an irrefragable Maxime, never <hi>Fidarſi al nemico reconciliato; To truſt a reconciled Enemy.</hi> They are ſo rooted and habituated to revenge, that in all the Towns belonging to this State, there is ſcarce any thing to be ſeen but perpetual Civil Wars. The <hi>Breſſians</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenza</hi> are ſo furious, and murders and aſſaſſinations ſo familiar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, it would ſcarce bring a Citizen out of his Shop, to ſee a man kill'd before his face, and they are ſo little concern'd at the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any man, that if they hear a Gun go off in the Street, the moſt pious perſon amongſt them will pull
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:110049:47"/>off his Hat, and ſay a ſhort Prayer for the murderers eſcape. And as if this were not enough, the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents adde this way of revenge to the education of their Children, ſhewing them conſtantly every night and morning the bloody Shirts in which their Predeceſſors were ſlain, inflaming their young veins with deſire of revenge, which encreaſing with their age, never abates, but with the utter ruine and deſtruction of their enemy.</p>
                  <p>And yet this liberty would not be altogether unpardonable, if they took but honourable wayes to atchieve their revenge: I call them honourable wayes, becauſe though there be Princes which have forbid Duels, yet upon any complaint they cannot conceal the difference they make betwixt a man that chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges, and one that refuſes. But their wayes are ſo barbarous, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:110049:47"/>baſe, they are not to be recited but with horrour. They entertain Garriſons of theſe <hi>Bravoes</hi> in their Houſes, who being arm'd exactly, are many times the perfidious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of their death, which they ought in gratitude to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; and in truth there is no people that I know more unhappy than theſe Nobles, the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Monk of them all not enduring half ſo much pain with their Hair and their Sackcloth, as theſe do with their Coats of Mail and their Corſlets, which for greater ſecrecy they wear commonly next their skin alſo. In ſhort, their lives are ſo diſturb'd and inquiet, by their paſſionate appetite of revenge on the one ſide, and their immoderate apprehenſion of danger on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the neareſt of their rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have many times fallen under their hands, in the fantaſtical a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:110049:48"/>harms they have created to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p>Their Wives (how vertuous and diſcreet ſoever they be) they uſe like the greateſt Criminals i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginable. They keep them lock'd up cloſe in their Chambers, which are fortified at all points, and not to be entred but thorow an iron Grate. They do not allow them the converſation of mankind, nor ſuffer them to be attended, but by their own Sex; and if they do not govern themſelves with the higheſt ſeverity, they run no leſs hazard than of their lives. For in this caſe they are ſo jealous, they will revenge the ſin of the Father upon his Children, and extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate a whole Family for the offence of a ſingle man: and yet for all this their Wives are Women, and <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> too.</p>
                  <p>This (according to my beſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation)
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:110049:48"/>is the life of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſs upon the <hi>Terra-firma.</hi> Some will tell me perhaps they cannot but admire, ſo prudent and potent a body as the Senate ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch abominable diſorders. But in this lyes the ſubtilty and neatneſs of their policy; for if they do not promote them on purpoſe, they at leaſt connive at their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, to the end that being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd in mining and countermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at home, they may be taken off from any publick contrivances, to the prejudice of the State. They know very well where there is a radicated and inveterate quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, there can never be an entire and ingenuous union, which of all things in the world this State is moſt apprehenſive of, as the moſt probable way for its ruine and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. And indeed conſidering how numerous and (in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect)
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:110049:49"/>conſiderable they are, ſhould they be unanimous, and live in any correſpondence, it were no hard matter for them to be too hard for their Maſters, and to tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them down headlong, that do now trample upon their necks. It is an ordinary ſaying at <hi>Venice,</hi> that this great body being full of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly and corrupt humours, nothing is more convenient for it than Phlebotomy, and that having that faculty of opening their veins for one another, they ſave them the labour of applying any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies. But beſides the aforeſaid advantages which the <hi>Venetian</hi> draws from theſe animoſities, there is another of which upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion they make conſiderable uſe, and that is by declaring any of theſe Gentlemen of the <hi>Terra-firma</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, if after they have ſatisfied their fury, and as it were glutted
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:110049:49"/>themſelves with the blood of their adverſaries, they begin to appear formidable in the Countrey, by the multitude of their <hi>Bravoes,</hi> or the quantity of their crimes. In ſuch caſe the Senate underſtands well enough that the perpetiation of ſuch and ſo numerous villanies, muſt of neceſſity create them ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies <hi>ad infinitum,</hi> and therefore without more circumſtance they baniſh this terrible offendor, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade him from his honours, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of his Eſtate, ſet a price upon his head, and having craved the aſſiſtance of all the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Countreys towards the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of juſtice, and engaged their concurrence in ſo equitable a Cauſe, they conſtrain the poor Tyrant to an unhappy dilemma, of either living obſcurely in ſome Cave for the future, or elſe in the higheſt deſpair to betake himſelf to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:110049:50"/>the Field: from whence it comes there are many times ſo great par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Banditi</hi> to be ſeen in their Territories. An incomparable Maxime to give juſt ſo much rein to the vitious, as ſhall make them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent and odious, that they may afterwards ruine them with univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal approbation, and beſides poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the people with a moſt ſacred opinion of their juſtice, and ſecure their Provinces againſt the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of the Continent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> A particular Diſcourſe upon ſome of their Maximes.</head>
                  <p>THat which the World looks upon as their Treaſure, is (really) no ſuch thing. Their
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:110049:50"/>wealth is ſuppos'd to conſiſt in great heaps of money, cramm'd up in ſome ſecret and ſecure place, from whence upon occaſion they draw forth ſuch immenſe ſummes of gold and ſilver as they judge ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the conſervation of their State. Their chiefeſt riches in their greateſt extremities, lyes in the affections of their Nobility and Citizens, there it is they meet with their inexhauſtible ſprings, it is they whoſe love to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and apprehenſion of forreign dominion, makes them poſt-pone all Conſiderations of particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and draw their ſwords as well as purſes in defence of their State. After the death of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <hi>Marcello,</hi> the loſs of <hi>Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos,</hi> and the fatal allay to their victory in the death of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ccinego,</hi> though the Republick was almoſt dazeled with thoſe blows, and as it
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:110049:51"/>were fainting with the loſs of ſuch laudable blood, yet they diſdain'd to ſupply themſelves any where but at home, and the generous <hi>Peſaro</hi> (ſince choſen <hi>Doge</hi>) was the firſt who in that general Conſternation rais'd up their declining courages, by a moſt honourable example, offring the Senate his whole reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new for five years, which was no leſs than ſixty thouſand Duckats <hi>per annum.</hi> This noble Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not only confirm'd the irreſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, encouraged the timerous, and ſupply'd their neceſſities for the preſent, but has put them into ſuch a poſture, they are not probably to be deſtroy'd by any but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p>For the more effectual execution of the Orders of the Senate, they have a grand Provoſt in <hi>Venice</hi> who wears a long ſcarlet Robe, and is called by them <hi>Conteſtabile,</hi> he is
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:110049:51"/>attended by certain <hi>Sbires,</hi> in the nature of our Archers, and his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is to ſuppreſs the inſolence of ſuch Raſcals as diſturb the ſecurity of the People. Nevertheleſs theſe <hi>Sbires</hi> dare not lay hands upon a Gentleman, and if at any time it be their duty to ſeize upon any of them, they throw their Cloaks o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their head, and muffling them up in that manner, they carry them to Priſon. The Office of theſe <hi>Sbiri</hi> is ſo ſlaviſhly miſerable, a Nobleman, Citizen, or Stranger, (let his condition be what it will) if he can prove him guilty of the leaſt offence, may ſtab or piſtol any of them, without any danger of being puniſh'd.</p>
                  <p>The Water and the <hi>Gondoloes</hi> are as ſo many Sanctuaries, no medling with any man there, no execution of Juſtice, a Criminal upon the Water is as ſecure againſt
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:110049:52"/>the Sergants, as a man behind a Mud-wall, is againſt the ſtab of a Pen-knife. The Houſes of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors are in like manner ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, that if the greateſt <hi>Banditi</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> but touch the threſhold of their Door, he is exempt, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure againſt any kind of violence: beſides theſe they have certain pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg'd places, in which no man is to be diſturb'd, and their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges are kept inviolable, but if they catch any of them out of their <hi>Aſilum,</hi> they are lyable to the Laſh, and away they go to Priſon. Fire-Arms are ſo peremptorily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden in this City, that 'tis an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable offence to wear any there, and he that makes uſe of them, if he be taken, dies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mercy: by which piece of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity they prevent many aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which otherwiſe would be too frequent in that place, The
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:110049:52"/>ſtab with a <hi>Stidetto</hi> (which is a kind of Dagger the <hi>Italians</hi> wear behind their Robes) is not ſo cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, for that ſport being acted man to man, and the blows mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and alternate, the <hi>Venetian</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns himſelf not ſo much where the combate is equal, and one may kill his enemy, as ſoon as his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my him.</p>
                  <p>Thus far I have entertain'd you with the pleaſantneſs of that City, and other Towns upon the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, as are happy and at peace, we have made ſome Obſervations upon them, and concluded (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our judgement) that notwithſtanding the diverſity in their age, humours, and qualities, their Unity and Concord is ſo great, there is no revolution to be ſuſpected in that Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
                  <p>But now the noiſe of Trumpets
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:110049:53"/>and Drums, the ſhouts and accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the Souldiers calling me away, I muſt fall down with them to the Iſland of <hi>Lio,</hi> where they are uſually embark'd. The Galleys and Gallions trick'd up with their Banners and Penons, and as it were ſunk and ſwallow'd up in the ſmoak of their great Guns, perſwades me the General may be embarking himſelf, and all theſe valiant men imploy'd upon ſome extraordinary Enterprize. It would be a ſhame not to be a Souldier amongſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny brave perſons, and I that have formerly learn'd my Trade amongſt them, (cannot leave them in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in any noble Expedition: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs while the Souldiers and Officers are preparing for their Voyage, and the generous Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier taking) leave, of his Miſtniſs, I ſhall have time to ſpeak a word or two of their Military Policy.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:110049:53"/>
               <head>THE MILITARY POLICY OF THE <hi>VENETIAN.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>The Second Book.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Militia in general.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat War of all profeſſions in the World is the moſt noble and honourable, is a thing ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably clear, God Almighty amongſt his Titles
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:110049:54"/>in the holy Scriptures ſeems to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect none more than to be called the <hi>God of battel, The Lord of Hoſts,</hi> &amp;c. and the weapon he moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly us'd for the deſtruction of his enemies was the ſword, which to this day diſcriminates betwixt the Souldier, and the reſt of the people. Kings (which are his Vicegerents upon earth) delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Title of <hi>Invincible,</hi> prefer it to all other Epethites whatever; and the Nobility would never be reckon'd the right arm of their Prince, if they were not naturally more valiant than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary.</p>
                  <p>The bravery which excites the Gentry of <hi>France,</hi> and makes them run voluntarily into ſo many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, is in that reſpect more honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable than the <hi>Venetians,</hi> the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility amongſt theſe being oblig'd by indiſpenſable neceſſity, (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:110049:54"/>the heads of that State) to do their own buſineſs themſelves; for being eternally jealous of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and afraid to put the ſword into their hands, who may poſſibly make uſe of it to their prejudice, they ſeldom imploy them in any conſiderable Command, and if at any time they be forc'd, it is with ſuch caution and reſtraint, that they ſeem rather to tye up their hands, than to put them in arms. But that their proceedings may be leſs obſcure, and their Military Methods tranſmitted more clearly, I ſhall begin with their chief Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and give a deſcription of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:110049:55"/>
                  <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of their</hi> Generaliſſimo.</head>
                  <p>THe Authority of the <hi>Generaliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimo</hi> is ſo abſolute from the very moment of his Embarkment, that during his Government (for three years) the Republick it ſelf can ſcarce take notice of his actions. His Cabbin is like a little Senate, from whence all Orders relating any way to the Wars do conſtantly iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue; and in ſome reſpects he might be call'd independant, were he not at the end of his Reign to give an account of his behaviour to the Counſel of Ten, to anſwer to ſuch Queſtions as ſhall be ask'd, to purge himſelf of ſuch Crimes as he
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:110049:55"/>may be accus'd of, and in defect of that, to ſuffer and be expos'd to the ſame puniſhment as the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the people. And it is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary thing there, if he has any enemy conſiderable, or has not demean'd himſelf with the civility expected, to fall under the laſh, and receive a ſevere chaſtiſement from the Counſel of Ten.</p>
                  <p>There are moſt commonly ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Generals in the ſervice of the <hi>Venetian,</hi> but with ſuch ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and dependance upon this, they receive their Orders from him, and his Command is their ſufficient direction: and this is a cuſtome far from the practice of any other part of <hi>Europe,</hi> where fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently by the multitude and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance of their Generals, they weaken their Armies, and render them rather diſ-membred than commanded. It is no eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:110049:56"/>(eſpecially if they be perſons of conduct and courage) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a ſincere amity and affection betwixt two plac'd in equal autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. For the jealouſie of being leſs eſteem'd than his Partner, thruſts him violently upon all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, and ſets his wits upon the Tenter, to find out ſome way or other of depriving him of honour, and working himſelf into the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the people: if they be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in their humours, one brave and adventrous, the other ſlow and deliberate, how is it poſſible ſuch diverſity ſhould conſiſt with any deſign, or produce any thing to the honour of the State? And of this, in the late Wars we have ſeen ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry examples, where theſe kind of diviſions have been ſo prejudicial, that more than one Army have been defeated, (or endanger'd at leaſt) for not being ſeaſonably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:110049:56"/>by thoſe who though they were diſtinct by their Commiſſions, ought nevertheleſs to have made but one body, ſeeing both had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken arms for the ſame intereſts. The ſatisfaction to ſee ones Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor beaten will not ſuffer a man ſometimes to come in to his reſcue, every one triumphing in the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes of his Rival. Battels at Sea are much more dangerous and uncertain than the Engagements upon Land; in thoſe, providence, diligence, and the knowledge of the Countrey, are the three things which give life and aſſurance to an Army, there upon any ſudden, or unexpected accident or advantage, their deliberation is ſhort, and their reſolution eaſie; but at Sea if any thing be to be debated, they cannot run immediately to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and they muſt attend the turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Wind, the coming in of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:110049:57"/>the Tide, (which perhaps is ſix hours too late) before they can be in a poſſibility of executing their Orders, inſomuch that many a fair Enterprize is loſt, which two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments before would have been glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and ſucceſsfull. For theſe Reaſons the Republick of <hi>Venice</hi> commits all to the <hi>Generaliſſimo,</hi> who has full power of himſelf to fight, retreat, or attempt any thing, that in his judgement may be honourable, or advantageous to the State.</p>
                  <p>The principal buſineſs of this omnipotent Office, is to prevent or interrupt the coming down of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Fleet from the <hi>Euxine Sea,</hi> into the <hi>Archipellago,</hi> to this purpoſe having got his Navy toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he places it behind certain deſart Iſlands, (of which that Sea is full) in manner of an <hi>Ambuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade,</hi> or elſe takes his Poſt in a
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:110049:57"/>ſtrait paſſage under the currant of the two Caſtles (<hi>Ceſtos</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos</hi>) by which the <hi>Turks</hi> muſt of neceſſity come, which is not to be done without diſorder, if the leaſt oppoſition be added to the ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and rapidity of the Sea. <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedos</hi> was formerly an incomparable advantage, where their whole Fleet might ride ſecurely at anchor, attend their motions with patience, and aſſail them upon occaſion with very probable ſucceſs, but the Treaſon of one of their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen depriv'd them of that, which was of univerſal importance to all Chriſtendome. I my ſelf was at that time in their ſervice, when that accident happen'd, and could perhaps give a particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the whole tranſaction, but I ſhall ſay no more, than that there are the Heads of four or five hundred <hi>French</hi> ſtill to be ſeen upon
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:110049:58"/>the Walls of the Caſtles, which ſeem to cry out for vengeance, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the perfidiouſneſs of thoſe who deliver'd them into their hands.</p>
                  <p>The place of the <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> upon any conſiderable Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is alwayes in the Van of his whole Fleet; no Ship being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted before him but the General of the Gulf, who alwayes begins the Charge. The <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi>'s Galley is conſtantly very rich, and having ſerv'd one General, never deſcends to his Succeſſor. The <hi>Ventian</hi>-Generals may (not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly) be ſaid to reſemble the ancient Conſuls among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> which Hiſtory has deſcrib'd to us marching alwayes in their Robes, and not putting them off in the very Criſis of the Battel. They are commonly perſons of choiſe experience and reſolution,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:110049:58"/>otherwiſe if they behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſhonourably, they are ſure to be puniſh'd ſeverely. They are not ſo preciſe and curious of their age, if they have merit and capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, tis ſufficient for their Election. The brave <hi>Moccinego</hi> who died with ſo much honour at the head of his Fleet, was not compleat five and thirty years old, and doubtleſs had he eſcap'd that misfortune, the great deſigns he had on foot, (which yet were eaſie with his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct) would queſtionleſs have ſucceeded, and advanc'd him to that height which his virtue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd. To ſpeak the truth, there were many, and thoſe conſiderable Errors in that Engagement, which I have heard many grave Captains enumerate and prove. The <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lott</hi> is the way which they make uſe of in the Election of this Officer, every one giving his Vote in a little
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:110049:59"/>Bowl. Upon theſe occaſions, the young Gentlemen of the City will endeavours all boldly as any of the reſt; and though there was great conteſt in the Election of <hi>Moccenigo,</hi> and the ancienter ſort carried it at firſt, yet the youth ſollicited ſo vigourouſly, in ſpight of all oppoſition they created him at laſt.</p>
                  <p>This Command is not perpetual, but conſtituted by the Republick <hi>pro re nata,</hi> when War is openly proclaimed, and the neceſſity of their affairs requires it; when they ceaſe, that Office ceaſes with them, and the principal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand devolves upon the General of the Gulf.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:110049:59"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The General of the Gulf.</head>
                  <p>THe General of the Gulf is a perpetual Charge, and (as a man may ſay) never expires, for the <hi>Venetians</hi> looking upon themſelves as ſoveraign in the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driatick Sea,</hi> (which is call'd the Gulf of <hi>Venice</hi>) maintain a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſquadron of Galleys, and men of War on foot, as well in peace as in war, to keep their Subjects in the Iſles of <hi>Dalmatia</hi> in obedience, to protect their Frontiers upon the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> and ſecure them from the ſurprizes of the <hi>Pirats</hi> and <hi>Corſaires,</hi> with which that Sea is grievouſly infeſted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:110049:60"/>The War in the Gulf is proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without quarter, no Priſoners are taken there, and that Captain who for compaſſion or advantage gives any of them their lives, loſes his own moſt certainly for his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. All the Renegadoes they meet with, are hang'd immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Main-yard, and if their Wives he in their company, they never part them: if any Chriſtians turn Pirats, and fall into their clutches, they run the ſame deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny infallibly, and by this impartial juſtice it is they preſerve their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion in the Gulf.</p>
                  <p>This being the moſt ancient of all their Officers, he has upon that ſcore the honour of commanding (as it were) the forlorn, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the firſt inſult upon the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, though otherwiſe he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the <hi>Generaliſſimo,</hi> and receives his Orders without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:110049:60"/>His Command is ſimply at Sea, and as ſoon as any of his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers are landed, they are out of his juriſdiction: yet among the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> he is reputed a very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Officer, upon whoſe conduct and integrity the peace of all <hi>Italy</hi> depends, that Countrey being (as every one knows) bounded on one ſide by that Sea, as high as <hi>Capo-d' Hiſtria.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>His authority extends no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>Zant, Cephalonia,</hi> and <hi>Corfeu,</hi> (the moſt remote Iſlands in the Gulf) he never ſets foot on ſhore, but upon ſome neceſſary, or very important occaſion. His ordinary ſtation in time of peace is either at <hi>Corfeu,</hi> the Gulf of <hi>Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> or <hi>Zant,</hi> which are three Ports of neceſſity to be paſs'd by all that go to <hi>Venice.</hi> This Squadron is a kind of an Out-guard, plac'd on purpoſe to break the firſt effort of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:110049:61"/>the enemy, to obſtruct their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and to give opportunity to the Countreys under their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection to put themſelves into a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of defence. When the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick is not engaged in any actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Wars, their young Nobleſs are ſent conſtantly to the General of the Gulf, to be educated in arms, and out of this Nurſery it is they are furniſhed with thoſe illuſtrious Officers, who ſo frequently and ſucceſsfully attempt the vaſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies of the <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this policy they reap two very conſiderable Effects: one is, they bring up their youth (as it were) in the lap of danger and War, and by a continual cuſtome of confronting them to the enemy, they give them ſuch a habit of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, as is never to be diſmai'd ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the potenteſt enemy, or the moſt terrible accident they can
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:110049:61"/>meet with. And yet the other is more conſiderable than this, enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them by degrees to an obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Equals, and not to mutiny againſt their Commands, by a ſottiſh pretence, <hi>That they are as good, and know as much as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> This I have ſeen in other places, but to ſpeak truth, it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſavours of a Souldier nor a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant man, who whilſt he lives will never decline any honourable action upon any occaſion whatever.</p>
                  <p>If the <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> dies, or comes to any unfortunate accident, the General of the Gulf ſucceeds him on courſe, and takes the Command of the Army without any contradiction; a wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent way to break the neck of all diviſions which might ariſe for the Command, which too often proves like a Plague in an Army, and deſtroys more men than the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies Sword.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:110049:62"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the General of their Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſſes, and their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</head>
                  <p>THis Command requires a man of reſolution and judgement, the whole ſucceſs of their Battels depending principally upon him. He has the Command (as a man may ſay) of the Bulworks which ſecure the Fleet, oppoſing his Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſſes as ſo many impregnable Ramparts againſt the fury of all at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taques, and when-ever he forces himſelf into the middle of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, he breaks their Squadrons, diſorders their Battaliaes, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces even victory it ſelf to declare for his party.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:110049:62"/>The Captain of every Galeaſs under his Command is call'd the Governour, to ſhew the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Charge with which he is entruſted, and that not imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, ſeeing in effect they are as ſo many floating Caſtles, in which they have commonly a thouſand men in Garriſon, who mount the Guards, and are reliev'd, take their ſeveral Poſts, keep their Sentinels, and go the Rounds with as much order and punctilio, as they uſe in our Citadels. They have each of them a hundred pieces of whole Canon, (which demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates their puiſſance when they are in a body) and by the help of their Sails and their Oars, they perform the ſervice both of the Gallies and Gallions, making their way in a calm by the force of their Oars, and by the benefit of their Sails, (with the leaſt gale of wind)
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:110049:63"/>they manage themſelves as nimbly as any other of their Ships.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Ships being of an unima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable expence, the <hi>Venetian</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertains no great number of them in his ſervice; the moſt I ever ſaw at one time together in their Fleet was but ſix, yet for fear of any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, they have ſeveral more in their Arſenal of this and all other ſorts ready to put to Sea. Their confidence in theſe Ships is ſo great, they conclude them invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, and a Town which has one of them to make good the entrance into its harbour, believes it ſelf ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and deſpiſes all other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection. The famous <hi>Tenedos</hi> had two of theſe Machines for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of its fortreſs, and certainly it had been ſafe, had they been kept to their ſtation, but the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his money having carried them away, the <hi>Baſſa</hi> found a way to carry the Iſland.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:110049:63"/>Beſides the Punctilio of honour which animates the Governours, they are under a neceſſity of being brave, or dying with infamy. This is it which makes them fight with reſolution, and neither take nor give quarter to any, if one of theſe Governours yields to five and twenty Gallies, (though the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber be ſufficient to fright a whole Fleet) he muſt have a care of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again into the clutches of the <hi>Venetian,</hi> if he does, the beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment he can expect is to have his head chop'd off in his own Ship, in the ſight of the whole <hi>Armada.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Never was any ſtranger entruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Command of the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſſes not but the Souldiers and Crew are generally forreign, and the Officers for the moſt part of the ſame Countreys with them; but all are ſubordinate to their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:110049:64"/>who receives no Orders but from his General, and the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral none but from the <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> himſelf. I might in this place give a Character of the ſeverity of their Military Laws, which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gives no body that is either Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard or Traytor: but it is ſcarce to be imagined, a man who has the ambition of putting for ſo great a Command, can want courage and reſolution to manage it when ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd: and when any of them are executed, 'tis not ſo much for their cowardiſe or fear, as for their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in betraying the good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conceiv'd of their Conduct. If we were but half ſo rigid in <hi>France,</hi> it would preſerve many a Town, and people would conſider very well how they engaged in a Command, that abus'd never ſo little would coſt them ſo dear. By this way the <hi>Venetian</hi> reaches
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:110049:64"/>his Officers to know them, yet he ſeldom puts theſe Charges into any mans hands, but ſuch as they are ſure are faithfull, and capable to manage them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the General of the Galli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Captains under his Command.</head>
                  <p>THeſe Gallions are alwayes commanded by a Gentleman of <hi>Venice,</hi> no other Nation being admittable to that Charge; the roguery of ſome forreigners who ran away with ſome of theſe Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels ready rigg'd, having taught them more wit than to truſt them for the future: but their Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Mechanicks are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:110049:65"/>of all Countreys. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they hire Ships of the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> or <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ready equip'd, and pay them every moneth, but they muſt be Commanded by a noble <hi>Venetian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The great Veſſels which they take now and then from the <hi>Turk,</hi> they call <hi>Sultans,</hi> and they are ſet out again at the expence of the publick: though the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a <hi>Sultan</hi> be in reality no more than the ſimple Captain of a Ship, yet he is more conſiderable, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing look'd upon as the mark of a particular eſteem, when one is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd to ſuch an authority as that.</p>
                  <p>And this they do to diffuſe an inſenſible jealouſie among their Commanders, recompenſing him whom they judge to have deſerv'd well, with the honour of a Charge, which has nothing in it above the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:110049:65"/>reſt, but an innovated name. In this particular they ſeem to imitate the example of the <hi>Romans,</hi> who (to animate their Souldiers) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented them with rewards, very trivial and inconſiderable to the eye, but (if meaſured with the honour they brought along with them to the party) they were vaſt accumulations of glory.</p>
                  <p>This General having all the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines of the Fleet on board his Gallions, he is of no mean impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance amongſt them, and to ſpeak truth no man is ever admitted to that Command till he has given undeniable evidence of his prudence and Conduct. They ſeldom come to grapple, or to a very cloſe fight with their enemy, but with their broad ſides they do terrible execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:110049:66"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of their Sur-Comites of the Gallies.</head>
                  <p>THat is the name by which they diſtinguiſh the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of their Galleys from their other Captains. They are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally young Gentlemen, who go on purpoſe to enure themſelves to the Wars, and make themſelves eminent by ſome remarkable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. The Hull, and materials of the Galleys are deliver'd out of the Arſenal, with all manner of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions both for the belly and the Wars, but the Rowers, the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and all manner of imbelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is at the charge of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:110049:66"/>As to their pay, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick diſcharges it from the time they are imbark'd, and to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence the expence of the Captain in ſome meaſure, he diſpoſes of all inferiour places in his Galley. There being alwayes an unſatiable emulation amongſt the young No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſs, this is the occaſion that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſtrives and contends with his whole force to out-do his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſignalize himſelf by ſome remarkable action. In their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins and Quarters there is no want of guilding or fine painting, and the rich Stuffs of which their<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Flags and Penons are made, demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates moſt clearly how unwilling they are to be out-done. In this manner the Republick appears moſt pompouſly ſplendid, at the charge of other people, and imploys the vanity and ambition of her young Gentlement, to her own magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and glory.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:110049:67"/>Before theſe newly equip'd Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys venture out to Sea, they are exercis'd by their Officers twice or thrice a day, betwixt the <hi>Place of St. Mark</hi> and <hi>Lio,</hi> and when their Superviſors think them capable of doing ſervice, within two or three moneths they are ſent away, not to the Fleet, but to the Squadron which is left behind for the ſecurity of the Gulf, and there it is they compleat and perfect their diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</p>
                  <p>The expence of their ſetting out being but ſuperficial, and the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy they have for their own contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, vaniſhing with the guilt and painting, which in a ſhort time the wind and the weather have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd, all the ambition they have left, is only to put themſelves as forward as their companions dare go, and it is no ſmall excitement to their courage, to conſider they
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:110049:67"/>hazard nothing of their own but their lives, the Republick being ready to furniſh them with ten new Galleys for one that is loſt. Whereas on the contrary if the Officers be Proprietors, their whole fortune depending upon their Veſſel, their intereſt will make them decline thoſe dangers, which perhaps their valour would attempt.</p>
                  <p>When theſe Galleys are Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded out to any Engagement, to advance into the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> and confine the <hi>Turks</hi> to the <hi>white Sea,</hi> they are re-inforc'd with forreign Souldiers, beſides what they had afore. They are diſtributed ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litickly into the Galleys, they cannot poſſibly get to a body, and diſpoſed with that artifice, a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſhall ſcarce ever have a dozen of his own Souldiers aboard the Ship where he is himſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:110049:68"/>Though this be a mark of their diffidence and diſtruſt, yet by this expedient they ſecure themſelves againſt the worſt; and it is poſſible they may do it to animate their Souldiers, that by making them ſuſpect they are jealous of their courage, they might be puſh'd forward the more to convince them of their miſtake: for doubtleſs he who can nettle his Souldiers in point of their honour, has no ſmall command of the courage of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. We have ſeen in our days ſeveral effects of this jealouſie, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in the firſt Wars in <hi>Flanders,</hi> in which the animoſity betwixt the <hi>Walloons</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> was the occaſion of the loſs of ſeveral Towns to the <hi>Hollander,</hi> which otherwiſe the experience or gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of their General would never have taken. But this variance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Souldiers precipitated
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:110049:68"/>their pains, haſtned their aſſaults, and by a happy temerity thruſt them upon that, which without thoſe Conſiderations they would have look'd upon as deſperate.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Captains wear their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Veſtments conſtantly, and are habited in their Galleys at the ſame rate as if they were in the <hi>Place of St. Mark,</hi> by which means they preſerve to themſelves the ſame reſpect as if they were in the Town. They retain the ſame pride and opinion of themſelves al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, for let things go as they liſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, they will alwayes be known to be Gentlemen of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice.</hi> Their Galleys are ſmall and light, of that ſort which they call <hi>Gall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Suttili,</hi> but ſomething more nimble and eaſie to manage, and they have generally aboard them the beſt Canoniers in the World. Their Canon in their Men of War
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:110049:69"/>ſeldom carry above thirty or forty pound Ball. Beſides the Canon aforeſaid, they have alwayes upon the Prow of the Ship four ſmall Guns, which their Canoniers will diſcharge as certainly, and with as ſure execution, as we can do with our <hi>Fuſils.</hi> Upon the ſides and flanks of the Ship they have other Engines of miſchief, but the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt hurt they do is with certain murdring peeces, (which they call <hi>Moſquetti a Cavaletto</hi>) that are plac'd upon the Steerage.</p>
                  <p>Their <hi>Bonnevoglies</hi> or Rowers are of great uſe to them upon any extremity, for being all of them Chriſtians, and accuſtomed to dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, they arm them (againſt any Engagement) with Stones and Cuttelaſſes, and promiſing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their pay, they make them ſupply the rooms of ſuch Souldiers as are kill'd. But the <hi>Turks</hi> dare
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:110049:69"/>not do ſo, for moſt of their Oats being Chriſtian Slaves, kept con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly in chains, and moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble captivity, they ſeldom dare ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard a Combate, their apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Slaves they have on board, being as terrible to them, as the enemy before their face.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Of the General or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Candia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THough his Command be ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon Land, yet I rank him amongſt the Officers of the Fleet, becauſe being in an Iſland he may be ſaid to be conſtantly at Sea. His authority is much the ſame as
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:110049:70"/>that of a Viceroy with us: it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued only for three years, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any ambitious deſigns which otherwiſe might be ſuggeſted by ſo eminent a Government.</p>
                  <p>He gives a punctual accompt of whatever is done in the Iſland, and though the principal Command be in him, he dares not enterprize any thing but by the Counſel, and conſent of ſuch perſons as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick have plac'd about him. Before their late Wars with the <hi>Turk,</hi> this was one of the moſt il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Commands belonging to this Commonwealth; but of late it is much leſſen'd, and reduc't to ſome few Towns which the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of <hi>Candia</hi> have left them.</p>
                  <p>Since the taking of that, they have only two places remaining, not very capacious, but conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their harbours and ſtrength, the Governour of each of them are
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:110049:70"/>nominated by the Governour-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. The Towns are called <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalonga</hi> and <hi>Suda,</hi> places of good retreat, in caſe of diſaſter. The ſituation of <hi>Spinalonga</hi> is admirable, and it was ſtrange to me to find it ſo ill provided with men. But I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their great confidence is in the Sea on one ſide, and the Rocks on the other.</p>
                  <p>In the Offices of <hi>Generaliſſimo,</hi> and General of <hi>Candia,</hi> they never put two perſons who are in perfect intelligence, leſt having the two Keys of the Commonwealth at their Girdle, they ſhould open the way to any deſign, and permit their ambition to enter.</p>
                  <p>Before the ſurrender of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis, his authority was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Military, but in Civil affairs, and he Order'd them both at his pleaſure, inſomuch that the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Majeſty of the Kings of <hi>Crete</hi>
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:110049:71"/>ſeem'd not to be altogether extinct, the Generals Court, his Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Habit, repreſenting no ſmall reſemblance of Royalty.</p>
                  <p>The forreign Generals who Commanded the Troops of the Iſland, had all of them their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from him, which were to be conſtantly obey'd, if not, they were left to his cenſure, but with appeal to the Senate, who are not ſubject to thoſe effluxions of paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as their Viceroys may be. In ſhort, they give him this authority to render him the more reſpected, and enable him to ſee the Orders tranſmitted to him, executed with more exactneſs. And doubtleſs were he not ſupported by this abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Command, which is no little terrour to the inferiour Officers, who are generally ſuch as have not been much acquainted with the Field, thoſe which have more skill
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:110049:71"/>in their profeſſion, would poſſibly undervalue his Orders, and from that negligence, grow by degrees inſolent and contumacious, which is the next ſtep to rebellion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of the General of <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THe General of <hi>Dalmatia</hi> has more Countreys and more Towns under his Command, than the General of <hi>Candia,</hi> and yet his Charge is not eſteem'd ſo honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as the other, for which cauſe I place him after the General of <hi>Candia,</hi> and amongſt the Officers of the Fleet, becauſe his authority extends it ſelf principally along the Coaſts of the Gulf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:110049:72"/>The chief Towns under his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are <hi>Zara, Cliſſa, Spalatro, Zebenico, Cattaro, Dulcingo,</hi> and others, beſides an infinite number of little Iſles, the Countrey of the <hi>Morlaiks,</hi> and the ancient <hi>Sclavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi> Theſe Countreys are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently inhabited with a laborious and warlike people, amongſt which the <hi>Morlaiks</hi> bear the Bell, and are eſpecially eminent. I muſt confeſs in all my Travels I never ſaw any Nation ſo ſubtil and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous at inroads and incurſions as theirs, nor that behaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves better upon any deſperate rencounter, but one of their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt encouragements is their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Mountains, with which they are perfectly well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted. They uſually incamp near ſome conſiderable Town with their Families and Cattel, without any military Order at all, and when
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:110049:72"/>they are threaten'd with a Siege, or find themſelves unable to keep the Field, they retire into the Town, and are no ſmall re-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement to the Garriſon.</p>
                  <p>The places aboveſaid are all of them conſiderable, and well forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, only <hi>Cattaro</hi> lyes under the Command of certain great Hills, which they call the <hi>black Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains.</hi> Nevertheleſs the entrance into the Harbour is ſecur'd by a ſtrong Caſtle, which facilitates the acceſs of ſupplyes, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence makes it no eaſie matter to reduce.</p>
                  <p>This General has the overſight of all theſe Towns, he ſuperviſes, and ſupplyes all their Magazines, he gives all Orders, and ſends out what parties or perſons he pleaſes, to make diſcovery of the Enemy. If at any time he conceives a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of performing any thing
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:110049:73"/>conſiderable, without being inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by the <hi>Turk,</hi> he draws out what Souldiers he thinks fit out of his Garriſons, (which are alwayes well furniſh'd) and forming them into a flying Army, he purſues his deſign. He has forreign Generals under him, as the General of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> had formerly, and Commands them with the ſame authority. If any conſiderable diſaſter happens within the compaſs of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, all is imputable to him, which is that which quickens his vigilance, and makes him more than ordinarily diligent and active.</p>
                  <p>The Baſſa of <hi>Boſnia</hi> is a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Neighbour of his, but he ſweetens him often with his <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quins.</hi> He pretends to have a great confidence in the people of that Countrey, who are very ſtout, and by that confidence he acquires their affection. He truſts ſuch
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:110049:73"/>Governments and Garriſons in their hands, as he has power to diſpoſe of himſelf, yet he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes accountable to the State; a ſure way to have good Officers, for he who is to anſwer for ſuch as he prefers, will not readily admit any that are incapable, nor open his eyes to any thing but deſert.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of the Grand-Captains.</head>
                  <p>HE who conſiders nothing but the duty of their places, will at firſt daſh believe theſe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains but Officers of peace. But though the Sword be not in their hands every hour of the day, yet they have no inconſiderable part
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:110049:74"/>in the Militia of this State.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are they who in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral precincts upon the <hi>Terra-fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> receive all the new Levies which are made in forreign parts, for the ſervice of this Republick; theſe are they which model and form them, and teach them their duties; theſe are they who ſee them muſter'd conſtantly every moneth, and by ſome little quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications encourage them in the ſervice. By the gravity of their diſcipline and comportment, they enure them to a more regular life, and more compoſedneſs in their manners: if they behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves otherwiſe than well, they puniſh them as ſeverely; but there is no quarter for one that runs from his Colours.</p>
                  <p>They keep an exact eye over all the Cavalry in their Garriſons, and will by no means ſuffer either
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:110049:74"/>Horſe or Arms to paſs Muſter that is not punctually paſſable. And as they are rigid on the one ſide, ſo are they as juſt on the other, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to a day what is due, and ſupplying them faithfully with whatever is Order'd them by the State. Being not much acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the management of Horſe, upon any general Muſter, or ſome ſuch <hi>Parade,</hi> they commonly are aſſiſted by a Marſhal, or other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienc'd Officer; for even in thoſe Shews only they are ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, one of theſe Grand-Captains at <hi>Padua</hi> would not believe me ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Commanding the <hi>Gens d' Armes</hi> of the <hi>Chevalier Gremonville,</hi> becauſe my Beard and Muſtachoes were not ſo large as he would have had them.</p>
                  <p>Their principal aim is, in the name of the Republick to make themſelves Maſters of the Towns
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:110049:75"/>where they are ſent, but with the greateſt ſweetneſs and inſinuation imaginable; for taking alwayes the moſt plauſible pretences that are conducing to their ends, they quarter the Souldiers apart by themſelves, to prevent (forſooth) their inſolencies to the people, and the diſorders might otherwiſe ariſe, by the inextinguiſhable antipathy which continually reigns betwixt a Souldier and a Citizen: but in truth it is for two other Reaſons:</p>
                  <p>The firſt is, that they may have alwayes a conſiderable body toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ready to preſent themſelves where the ſafety or advantage of the Commonwealth requires, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when they are ſeparate in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Streets, and remote places, it is not eaſie to get them together in a ſhort time, without giving the Enemy advantage by this diviſion and delay. Beſides nothing being
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:110049:75"/>ſo natural to a Souldier as debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, when they have no retreat or place to return to, where they are afraid to be ſeen, nothing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages them ſo much to be licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, or occaſions more inſolence and diſorder.</p>
                  <p>The other is, to take away all means from the Nobility and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the Town to conſpire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Souldiers, and (by ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing them) to commence a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and that with the more eaſe, in reſpect that they have cut off the greateſt part of their oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They have heard the Story of the <hi>Sicilian Veſpers</hi> and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding well the <hi>Italian</hi> humour, (which is their own) they are jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of all the World, and for that reaſon they keep exact Guards within their quarters night and day. In their <hi>Carnivals</hi> and dayes of Recreation, in which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:110049:76"/>plauſibly hinder their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies and Maſquerades, that might give opportunity perhaps to ſome pernicious deſign. Under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of preſerving the peace, and preventing particular quarrels and aſſaſſinations, which in thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes might be perpetrated with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcovery, they draw what Forces they have into the Town, clap Guards in the moſt important places, ſecure the Avenews, and Commanding the remainder both of Horſe and Foot to follow, they go up and down the whole City viſiting the Balls and Dancings, where they obſerve the greateſt Confluence of people.</p>
                  <p>By this admirable artifice they make themſelves Maſters where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they come, and divert the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the moſt turbulent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits from attempting any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the State, by rendring it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:110049:76"/>for them to have any ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
                  <p>For their Souldiers in the <hi>flat Countrey</hi> they have another policy, which is both ſubtil and good: that they may be well diſciplin'd, ready for ſervice, and their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber known exactly, they have a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Muſter every moneth, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Countrey upon the <hi>Terra-fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> they levy new men, appoint them their Officers, deliver them arms, Command them to be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, and treat them very graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with the Title of <hi>Signori Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dati, Gentlemen Souldiers:</hi> but they pay dear enough afterwards for thoſe two honourable words, and I am perſwaded they do it on purpoſe to make them weary of the Wars. If the weather be worſe than other at any time either in Summer or Winter, they will be ſure to Muſter them in that,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:110049:77"/>and that they may be certain to have their ſhare of it, they will appoint their Rendezvouz in ſome open and deſart Plain, where the Sun (which in Summer is very vehement in thoſe parts) and the Snow and Cold (which is no leſs troubleſome in Winter) have their full play at them, and do ſo torture the poor Peaſant, that there is nothing they have in the whole World, but they will give to have their Names put out of their Rolls. If (beſides their arms which are very heavy) they carry no Provant along with them, they may return a hungry, for any care is taken of them, it being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbid that any Victuallers or Subtellers appear in the place of their Rendezvonz. Their arms are not entruſted with them after their Exerciſe is done, they have only the priviledge of bringing
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:110049:77"/>them back upon their ſhoulders, and delivering them up to their Grand-Captain at their return. By this ſeverity they tire out thoſe poor Creatures, and make them abominate the Trade of a Souldier, which is indeed no more than what the <hi>Venetian</hi> deſigns.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of their Forreign Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals.</head>
                  <p>THe Commanders which we have hitherto preſented, are choſen out of the body of the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Nobility, for a long ſucceſſion of time there having ſcarce one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon been entruſted with thoſe Charges. Nevertheleſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:110049:78"/>on occaſion they have been neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to have recourſe to Strangers, and to give them conſiderable Commands, either becauſe they believe the <hi>Tramontani</hi> (which is the name they call all Strangers by) more vigorous and active than their own Countreymen, or elſe that they deſire to preſerve their own Nobility, keeping them ſtill for the chiefeſt and moſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble imployments, and committing all things of peril and danger to the conduct of Forreigners; in which reſpect they are not very niggardly of the Title of General, of which ſort they will create ſeveral accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their neceſſities, and the quality or ambition of the perſons they entertain. And in this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber there are three extraordinary, The General of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of the Forces Commanded on ſhore, and the General of <hi>Candia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:110049:78"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> The Forreign General in <hi>Dalmatia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NExt to the Proveditor-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, (which is a noble <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi>) this Forreign General is the chief perſon both in the Countrey and Army, and has the Command of all the Militia, but ſo as he can do or attempt nothing but by the conſent of the Proveditor, in whoſe abſence he gives all Orders both in the Field and the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: and it is remarkeable, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be choſen on purpoſe of different humours, or that the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie inherent to their Command ſuffers them not to agree) they
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:110049:79"/>are never in any great intelligence with one another, and yet (which is moſt ſtrange) never at ſo much odds as to prejudice the State.</p>
                  <p>One thing in my judgement is ſomething ſtrange in this Charge, and that is the ſmall authority this General has, for beſides the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and formalities pay'd him by the Souldiers, he has not the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to gratifie any of his men with a dayes pay, or a loaf of bread more than their due, but by the expreſs Order of the Proveditor, and when he does, it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly out of his own purſe.</p>
                  <p>The Souldiers for the moſt part having greater difference and reſpect for the perſon who in all dangers is conſtantly at their head, fights a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them perpetually, and bears his ſhare in all the difficulties they endure, the Proveditor (who thinks it beneath him to live in that
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:110049:79"/>Community) keeps a conſtant eye upon the actions of his rival, and by the Soveraign authority with which he is endued, reſtrains any exorbitance that might flow from their affection.</p>
                  <p>In this manner they allow the Forreign General power enough to Command the Army, and to March them out when he pleaſes, yet with ſuch reſtriction, it is clear they intend all ſhould depend upon the <hi>Venetian,</hi> and that the honour of all noble atchievements ſhould devolve upon him, as well as the power of puniſhments and rewards, as he is Commander in chief. Hence it is that the Souldier receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing but from his hands, believes he is to ſerve nothing but the Commonwealth, and obeys his Outlandiſh General for no other reaſon but becauſe he Commands for them; a policy by which they
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:110049:80"/>are ſure to be Maſters, let who will Command, and ſecures them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any apprehenſion of making of parties. <hi>Don Camillo Gonzague</hi> was General in this nature, the laſt Campagnia I made in their ſervice, he died as he was upon his return at <hi>Capo d'Iſtria,</hi> not without ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of having taken a Pill.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall ſay nothing of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of <hi>Candia,</hi> he being but another arm, which receives its life and agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation from the ſame head as the other. Some of theſe Generals have been puniſh'd ſeverely, and particularly the late Monſieur <hi>de la Valette,</hi> who was made an eminent example of the power of their Chiefs, when they repreſent the body of their Republick, and it will not be long before the <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier de Gremonville</hi> will be able to tell ſome Stories of his own.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:110049:80"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the General of the Forces drawn out of the Fleet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion.</head>
                  <p>THe moſt conſiderable ſtrength of the <hi>Venetian</hi> are his Forces at Sea, which may be call'd their great Outguards, plac'd on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to reſiſt and repel any ſudden or impetuous inſult, which their Enemy might make. In <hi>Candia</hi> and <hi>Dalmatia</hi> they do but fence, and put by the Paſſes which the <hi>Turks</hi> make upon them, and if they loſe nothing in a Campania, they think themſelves happy enough: but in their Fleet it is clear other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:110049:81"/>they fight, they attacque, they ſearch for their Enemy, and if they find him not at Sea, they invade him upon Land, penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſometimes into the very heart of his Countrey, and making the moſt remote corners of his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons tremble for fear, as much as thoſe places which are adjacent to the Sea.</p>
                  <p>But foraſmuch as all the <hi>Venetian</hi> Commanders have (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) their particular imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which they dare not deſert; and a <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> cannot abandon his Fleet, or leave it engaged in the middle of his enemies, they have their recourſe to their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Generals, who have the Command of ſuch Forces as are to be drawn out of the ſeveral Ships, upon any emergent deſign. <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur le Chevalier Gremonville</hi> ſerv'd them in this capacity with as much
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:110049:81"/>honour and ſucceſs as his courage and virtue required. <hi>Natolia</hi> can very well witneſs what I ſay, where we who were upon that acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaw him (though wounded with a Musket-ſhot) ſhewing and directing (with his Sword and his blood) the way to overcome, to thoſe who followed him at the ſiege of <hi>Schiſmeſet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The deſign upon Land being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, or defeated, as ſoon as the Commanded Forces are returned to their Ships, the General lays down his authority, and retains no more than the Title of Excellence, which the proudeſt <hi>Venetian</hi> of them all will not refuſe him, and this is the only lenitive that makes him ſwallow his degradation, and endure to walk croſs-armed upon the Decks without any Command. True it is, upon any new Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he has authority as before, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:110049:82"/>if he be in any favour with the <hi>Generaliſſimo,</hi> then he has much more reſpect in the Army, and is careſs'd as a perſon likely by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and conduct to procure great advantages to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, who to ſpeak truth ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom advances any to that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but ſuch as are well skill'd in military affairs.</p>
                  <p>Their enterpriſes are commonly deliberate, but their executions very quick, leſt they ſhould give the <hi>Turks</hi> (who ſwarm all along the Coaſts of the <hi>Archipelago</hi>) opportunity to put themſelves in arms, and hazard the being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid by their innumerable multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and beſides, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to have their Souldiers and Officers any long time out of their Ships, for fear leſt a good gale of wind ſhould bring their enemies Fleet amongſt them, which they might think further off.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="155" facs="tcp:110049:82"/>At the beginning of the Wars, theſe Generals were very well pay'd, but at preſent they are not ſo punctual; either that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction of the War has exhauſted their treaſure, or that they think to engage them the better to their ſervice, by keeping them in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual hopes of receiving a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſumme together: and perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to take away all means from them of ingratiating with the Souldier by their largeſſes and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, which conſidering the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their pay, they might poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly attempt, if it were conſtantly pay'd them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:110049:83"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Of the Governour of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BEſides the forreign General in <hi>Candia,</hi> there is a particular Governour in the Town, who to ſpeak properly has the only Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Town, the Generals authority being in the Field, and the Governours in the Garriſon.</p>
                  <p>The noble <hi>Venetian</hi> (who is as Viceroy of this Iſland) has theſe two Officers under him in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of his Lieutenants, to whom he commits the care and the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but retains the glory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to himſelf. He derives his Orders to the Governour, and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:110049:83"/>the Governour to the Officers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him. His juriſdiction reaches no further than the Walls of the Town, and his buſineſs is to have an eye over the Gates, to ſee his Guards accommodated, and in good order, to keep his Petrols conſtantly in the night, to keep his Souldiers to their duty, to fortifie where it is wanting, to repair what is decay'd, to prevent or ſuppreſs all diſorders, and give an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of occurrences to the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy.</p>
                  <p>In fine, all theſe Charges how great and conſiderable ſo ever they may appear, are notwithſtanding ſo ſubordinate and depending, that thoſe who enjoy them may be ſaid to pay as much obedience to ſome people, as they receive from others themſelves upon emergency or neceſſity. There are other Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals choſen to Command the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:110049:84"/>Horſe; and to gratifie the ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their ſuitors, they divide their Infantry into two bodies, (the <hi>Italian,</hi> and Forreign) and make a diſtinct General over each of them. The Artillery likewiſe has its proper General, and indeed when they have occaſion for good Officers, and can be ſure to keep them under, they do not ſcruple to give them what Titles they deſire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIV.</hi> Reflexions in manner of a Recapitulation.</head>
                  <p>THeſe variety of Generals would make one at firſt ſight expect more confuſion than order in their Militia; but all is mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:110049:84"/>with the ſame juſtice and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs, as they were but ſo many members moved and actuated by one head. Their Territories be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing large and remote, they are forc'd to divide their Commands, and according to the example of the firſt Commonwealths, they give the ſame authority to their Generals in <hi>Candia</hi> and <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> both in Civil and Military affairs, as the <hi>Romans</hi> in ancient times granted to the Pro-Conſuls in their ſeveral Provinces.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> at Sea ſeems to entrench ſomewhat too much upon the Liberty of the Republick, his immenſe power reliſhing more of the Soveraign than the Subject. But if we reflect upon the people about him, (who yet behave themſelves towards him with all vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſubmiſſion) we ſhall find them ſo great ſharers in his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:110049:85"/>that ſhould he meditate the leaſt miſchief imaginable to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the State, or go about to inſiſt upon his own force and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, he would be deſerted in a moment, and not one conſiderable man left with him to carry on his deſign. Moreover, not being Maſter of any one Town, he muſt be conſtrained to keep the Sea per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually, or at length in the higheſt deſpair, to caſt himſelf for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection into the hands of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which would be a ſad effect of an exorbitant ambition.</p>
                  <p>The private lives which theſe great perſons are to lead when their Commiſſions are expired, and the ſtrict account they give to the <hi>Counſel of Ten,</hi> keeps them conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in awe. They know very well that Court is inflexible, and when thoſe great Titles and nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ornaments are taken away,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:110049:85"/>they ſhall be liable to the cenſure of every Mechanick. For this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon every man looking upon his Neighbour as his enemy, they grow to ſuch a habit of jealouſie, they diſtruſt all the World, and not daring to deviate for fear of being impeach'd, they regulate all their actions for the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth.</p>
                  <p>When they admit any Stranger to their principal Commands, tis rather to participate of the peril than the honour, which they are tender of to the higheſt degree, and therefore they require ſo ready and ſo rigid a ſubmiſſion to all their Orders, that it is capital either not to execute them at all, or not to give them the glory when they have. <hi>Raillery</hi> and jeſting, though innocent in it ſelf, and the moſt common diverſion of the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> in other parts, is ſo peremptorily
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:110049:86"/>forbidden here, that it is look'd upon as a great want of reſpect, and provokes theſe hot-Spurs (who are puff'd up with their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority) ſo highly, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a great deal of ſubmiſſion and addreſs to recover their favours.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of their Armies in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</head>
                  <p>THeſe Armies, governed and regulated by their military Laws, may without a Soleciſm be ſaid to be moving Cities, wall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with their ſwords, their ſhields, and their arms; for as in a City they live not in confuſion or diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but the diverſity of Charges
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110049:86"/>diſtinguiſhes betwixt the ſoveraign Magiſtrate and the inferiour, as likewiſe betwixt them, and the reſt of the people: and for the better harmony and motion of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, a Chief is commonly choſen, upon whoſe ſhoulders they repoſe the whole care of the Publick; ſo in Field they take the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. The General is the firſt Mover which gives the ſwing and twirl to the reſt of the great Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, who convey it to the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and ſo it goes round. In this laſt military Order we have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the moſt conſiderable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, but honour not being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the aim of all people, moſt part of the Souldiers having taken themſelves to that courſe of life for their intereſt and profit, it falls out ſometimes, that failing of their pay, and the rewards they expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they complain, they threaten,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:110049:87"/>and at laſt run into an abſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. The length of the War is the thing many times which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces theſe diviſions, the exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive expence they are at, diſables them to keep their word with their Souldiers, and puts them upon a neceſſity of ſubſtracting themſelves from their ſervice. The converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they have with the Women of the Countrey where they are, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauches them, and prevails with them to marry, in hopes of having a <hi>Camarade,</hi> and fellow-ſufferer in their ſorrows, but they find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves removed out of Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing into the warm Sun, and that they have but augmented their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, by obliging themſelves to provide for their Families, when they were not able to provide for themſelves. Nevertheleſs among the <hi>Venetians</hi> there is no ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs, they pay their own
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:110049:87"/>Souldiers exactly, and have by that means hitherto prevented ſuch diſorders.</p>
                  <p>In the Garriſons upon the <hi>Terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firma</hi> they pay their Souldiers eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moneth, and they are ſo far from having any Debentures, they are alwayes in arrear to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. In <hi>Candia</hi> and <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia</hi> 'tis poſſible they are not ſo punctually pay'd, but at long run, if they do it not in money, they pay them in ſuch Commodities as will paſs in thoſe Countreys at a certain rate. The Generals ears are open to the complaint of a Souldier againſt his Officer, and redreſſes him where he is injured, but it is with ſo admirable equity, that he maintains the rights of the one, without deſtroying the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and diſtance of the other. Their Armies conſiſt principally of Foot, for having had experience of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:110049:88"/>how little importance their Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was to them in ſuch mountanous and unpaſſable places, they enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſome few Companies, more for the name of having Horſe, than for any great ſervice they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of their Cavalry.</head>
                  <p>THeir Cavalry is divided into two ſorts, Their <hi>groſs Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or Cuiraſſiers, which are like our <hi>Gens d' Armes,</hi> and their <hi>Cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets á Cheval,</hi> like our light Horſe, and the Commands of theſe two bodies are never ſold. In the time when I was in their ſervice, they had three Companies of theſe <hi>Gens
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:110049:88"/>d' Armes,</hi> which were called <hi>Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tramontani,</hi> and not one <hi>Italian</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to be amongſt them. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly this Republick confers theſe Commands upon ſome of their Forreign Generals, in lieu of ſome conſiderable pay, or in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of ſome remarkeable piece of ſervice. Theſe Governours of the <hi>Cuiraſſiers</hi> (for ſo it is they are called) have the nomination of their Captain-Lieutenants, their Cornets, and other inferiour Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, but they firſt preſent them to the Senate for approbation, which method <hi>Monſieur le Chevalier Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monville</hi> us'd, when he gave me my Command under him.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Italian</hi> Cuiraſſiers are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to four Companies, every one of them is oblig'd to keep his Horſe and his arms fix'd and in good order, and ſuch as are lazy and negligent are ſure to be puniſh'd
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:110049:89"/>at the next Muſter, which for the moſt part is every forty dayes. They have alwayes a conſtant Guard about their Standard, where-ever they are quarter'd, and to ſpeak truth, theſe are like Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers indeed, perpetually in the ſame poſture, as if they were in the very face of their Enemy. Their Diſcipline is the ſame with the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> they march, wheel, and draw off very cloſe and entire. Each Company conſiſts of ſixty men ſo brave and well order'd, there is ſcarce any attempt ſo diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, but may be thought feaſible by them. That Officer which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us is call'd a <hi>Marſhal des Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis,</hi> is term'd by them a <hi>Quarter-Maſter,</hi> and every Brigade has its Corporal to overlook it. They are arm'd <hi>Cap-a-pied</hi> when they go to the Wars, their Carbines and Swords by their ſides, and their
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:110049:89"/>Piſtols at their Saddle-Bow. The firmneſs and conſtancy of theſe <hi>Gens d'armes</hi> is ſufficient to diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the moſt reſolute of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; but the principal uſe of them is to keep their ground, and ſecure their Foot, not being able to keep pace with the light Horſe in their inroads into the Countrey, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the weight of their arms, and the heavineſs of their Horſes.</p>
                  <p>They are never ſent all of them to the Army, but they go accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ranks, and are there more for ſhew than any thing elſe. The <hi>Turks</hi> are nevertheleſs very fearfull of engaging them, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon their cloſe and firm way of fighting admits no impreſſion, how furious ſoever their Charges be made. Being cover'd with good arms, the <hi>Turkiſh Sabre</hi> does but little execution, and their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks being ſhort, they are quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:110049:90"/>repell'd. They ſtand their ground, and receive the Enemy very ſteadily, never diſcharging their <hi>Carabines</hi> till they be within ten or twelve paces. When they fall in, the ſervice grows bloody, for having fired their Piſtols, they fall to it with their Swords, which being broad and long, does the miſchief both of a Coutelas and a Tuck.</p>
                  <p>That they might not nouriſh a plague in their bowels, which might be able at length to corrupt the whole body, they caſhier all Souldiers which do not live honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, and in order. They uſe no other way of chaſtiſement, leſt they might irritate their old Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers by the ignominious ſpectacle, if they ſhould hang one of their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marades.</hi> The old Generals have a great eſteem for them, and uſe them very kindly, which tyes their
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:110049:90"/>affections inſeparably to them, and their pay being more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, it is not ordinarily known that any of theſe Souldiers forſakes his Company.</p>
                  <p>For their conveniencies upon all long marches, the Towns, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, and Villages where they paſs, are oblig'd to furniſh them with Waggons for their Baggage and Train, and they do it the more willingly, becauſe their marchis ſo innocent, one would take it rather for a Religious Proceſſion, than the motion of an Army, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deviating from the High-way, and where there is a neceſſity of paſſing thorow the Corn, they make the loſs good to the Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor immediately. The name of a Plunderer is ſo horrid amongſt them, it is known only by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay. They are very well accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated where-ever they come,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:110049:91"/>and they behave themſelves to their Landlo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds as to their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar friends.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of their Light Horſe.</head>
                  <p>THeir Light Horſe at preſent conſiſt of <hi>Sclavonians, Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matians,</hi> or <hi>Morlaicks,</hi> and are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by Companies, not by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments, as in other parts of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope;</hi> all of them are Subjects of this Commonwealth, as well as their Officers. They are all very ſtout, but not ſo well diſciplin'd, never keeping any ranks upon a charge, but falling on pell mell, after the manner of the <hi>Croats.</hi> True it is, they rally with great
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:110049:91"/>dexterity, but in the heat of the charge they conſider nothing but their paſſion, and advance or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat according to their own hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and fancy.</p>
                  <p>So many heads of the <hi>Turks</hi> as they bring home, ſo many <hi>Sequins</hi> are punctually pay'd them, and being naturally very covetous, they expoſe themſelves deſperately to catch them. They are a people will endure much hardſhip, and their Horſes (though ſmall) will endure as much as their Maſters. The moſt uſual way of their fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is by making inroads upon the Enemy, and infeſting thoſe Countreys which lye neareſt their borders. The Priſoners they take, belonging to the Republick, and the Souldier having no proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in them, is the occaſion they give no quarter, and the War is ſo inhumane.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="174" facs="tcp:110049:92"/>Our Dragoons have borrow'd the faſhion of their Caps from theſe <hi>Capelets,</hi> their ordinary arms are Carabines, and broad Swords, ſome of them have Piſtols, but the generality two or three <hi>Coutelaſſes,</hi> one faſten'd under each of their thighs, and another by their ſides. They never were acquainted with the uſe of Boots, and that which ſupplyes them is a ſort of Trowſes, button'd up cloſe to their legs, which ſerves them with leſs incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience.</p>
                  <p>It is a policy of no little impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the <hi>Venetian,</hi> to ſet this price upon the heads of the <hi>Turks:</hi> two conſiderable advantages accrew to them by it; by the hopes of a pittifull gain theſe Nations are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to a continual purſuit of the Enemy, and by giving no quarter to them, brought to a condition of expecting none themſelves, by
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:110049:92"/>which means all the commerce that might be apprehended from ſuch neighbouring Nations, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented or broken. Nor is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inferiour, this manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding rendring them deſperate and formidable where-ever they come. This kind of War may ſeem barbarous at firſt, but if the difference in Religion be conſider'd, that 'tis Empire they fight for, and that nothing is expected on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide but utter deſtruction, no wonder if their meaſures be ſo rigid and pernicious.</p>
                  <p>Not long ſince they made uſe of forreign Horſe in <hi>Dalmatia</hi> and <hi>Candia,</hi> but to ſpeak truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the exceſſive expence in which they involv'd themſelves thereby, they receiv'd but little ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, for the Countreys being bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and mountainous, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence unfit to ſuſtain them,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:110049:93"/>many of them periſh'd betwixt the legs of their Horſes, by the quality of a Climate to which they had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been accuſtom'd. The incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of furniſhing them both with Straw and Hay for their Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by Sea, made the <hi>Venetian</hi> wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſo unprofitable a Squadron, eſpecially when they found the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages they receiv'd by their <hi>Capelets,</hi> more conſiderable than all the great noiſe of their <hi>Calvary;</hi> for knowing the Countrey, being brought up, and accuſtomed to the Mountains, and acquainted with all the turnings and by-wayes that belong to them, they are upon the backs of the Enemy, before the old Cavalry could be got to their Colours.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="177" facs="tcp:110049:93"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Of their Infantry.</head>
                  <p>THe principal ſtrength of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Army conſiſts in their Foot, and the reaſon that makes them of greater eſteem, is the ſame that makes them enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſo few Horſe. The Infantry have their <hi>Meſtres de Camp,</hi> and diſtinguiſh'd Regimentally, as they are among us: it is made up of all Nations indifferently, but divided into two bodies, <hi>Italian,</hi> and Strangers, which is principally contrived, when they have a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of more than ordinary merit which they would Create General. Their arms are Musket and Pike,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:110049:94"/>and each Regiment beats its March according to its own Countrey. Theſe Forces are for the moſt part <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Swiſſes;</hi> and 'tis not a little remarkeable, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the fierceneſs and almoſt intemperate zeal which the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> profeſſes for the Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, there has not been one of them ſeen in the late Wars, which has aſſiſted this Commonwealth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> or ventur'd the leaſt drop of their blood in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Chriſtianity.</p>
                  <p>Under pretence of making new Levies continually, they keep moſt of their Colonels upon the <hi>Terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firma:</hi> I could not readily appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the reaſon of it, but at length (recollecting how jealous they were) me thought it was to take away or prevent the Regiments ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuch Officers as they fancied themſelves, and on the other ſide
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:110049:94"/>to keep them in their hands, (as it were ſo many hoſtages) that they might not be able to act any thing contrary to Orders. It may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they were unwilling to diſguſt their Camp Maſters, by drawing out too many of their men, and give them occaſion to complain, that of their whole Regiment, they have not ſometimes above thirty left.</p>
                  <p>Generally-all their Souldiers are in Garriſon, either in <hi>Candia,</hi> or <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and they have no other Forces conſtantly in pay, beſides their Army at Sea, which is re-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd out of the ſaid Garriſons as they have occaſion. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands amongſt their Foot are moſt commonly ſold, and yet they do not forbear rewarding any perſon who has ſerv'd them faithfully and long. Their pay is exact, and if they make th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m attend ſometimes
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:110049:95"/>by accident, they have it faithfully at laſt. Beſides a proportion of bread, and eight pence a day, they have a ſufficient quantity of wine allowed to each man: but that which qualifies all, is, when-ever they are Liſted, (unleſs they have very good fortune indeed, or more ſubtilty than ordinary) they many bid <hi>adien</hi> to the liberty of ever ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own Countrey again.</p>
                  <p>In this particular I cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their Politicks, for without doubt if they would give their Souldiers more liberty, though at firſt more of them might run away, than do at preſent, nevertheleſs it would extinguiſh the ill report they have all over <hi>Europe,</hi> of keeping their Souldiers in chains; and their good and punctual pay would invite them more ſtrongly, than their freedom would encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them to eſcape. Nay, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:110049:95"/>their vigilance and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, they loſe good quantities of them ſometimes, who chooſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to turn Renegadoes, and throw themſelves into the arms of the <hi>Turks,</hi> than to ſee themſelves under ſuch violence and reſtraint, by the loſs of their liberty, which perhaps (had the way been open) they would never have thought on: ſo ungovernable and ill-natured are the paſſions of Mankind, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing with that vehement impatience ſo much, as what is moſt ſtrictly forbidden.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lio</hi> is a place not far from <hi>Venice,</hi> where they put their Souldiers on Ship-board as ſoon as they arrive, and where they firſt begin to be ſenſible of their bondage. They put them all together in a large room, the windows fortified with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out with great bars of Iron, and the Sea encompaſſing them quite,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:110049:96"/>gives them the firſt proſpect of their impriſonment, and makes them (by its impoſſibility) not only apprehenſive, but deſperate of their liberty. If any mans rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or curioſity carries him to ſee them, he looks upon them (as they do upon the wilde beaſts at <hi>Vincennes</hi>) thorow an iron Grate, and inſtead of finding them jocund and merry, he meets with nothing but ſadneſs upon their faces, and lamentation upon their tongues. Nevertheleſs the receipt of ſome ſmall advance-money, and the conſideration of their Commons, (which is probably better than they have at home) renders theſe poor Creatures inſenſible of what they would otherwiſe abhor.</p>
                  <p>The ſervice of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth being under ſuch a ſcandal, they are many times neceſſitated to put their invention upon the rack,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:110049:96"/>for wayes of ſupplying themſelves when they want any men. They buy them very dear of their Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, who (if it be no Soleciſm) are no better than Horſe-courſers of men. The Princes their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours furniſh them alſo at their own rates, but they are fain to wheedle them in, and to perſwade them they are to lye perpetually in Garriſon, and never to be expos'd to the hardſhips of the Field. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, the Dukes of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> and <hi>Modena</hi> drive the principal Trade: they embark them upon the <hi>Po,</hi> in their great cloſe Boats they call <hi>Bourchij,</hi> clap good ſtrong Guards upon them at both ends of the Veſſel, and in this poſture without any arms they are conduct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Lio,</hi> (as ſo many Criminals) to be diſtributed into Companies when they come there.</p>
                  <p>They never put any of their
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:110049:97"/>Souldiers to death, becauſe they will not willingly loſe one man they may have occaſion to uſe: if they commit any crime conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they are condemn'd to the Gallies, and if their offences are ſmaller, their puniſhments are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned. Their <hi>Capelet Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> is the only Foot they truſt with the keeping of ſuch Towns as are on the Coaſt of <hi>Italy,</hi> and if there be any Strangers to be ſeen there, it is only in ſuch Towers as lye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently for their tranſportation to <hi>Lio.</hi> They make uſe of their own Subjects but very ſeldom, for a Levie in their own Countrey is rarely to be ſeen, perhaps they are apprehenſive that enuring them to the Wars, or accuſtoming them to Arms, may ſometime or other contribute to their ruine, and if at any time they imploy their <hi>Capelets,</hi> (under pretence of a particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:110049:97"/>in them) they are ſure to ſend them far enough for doing any miſehief.</p>
                  <p>To careſs and cajole the <hi>Morla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks,</hi> (which is a reſolute and active Nation) they give them leave in the winter time to retire into the Plains, and to quarter themſelves as near the Towns as they think convenient, pretending to ſecure them againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> but the truth of their deſign is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to have them under their power, and to re-enforce their Garriſons with them upon any ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den irruption. Theſe <hi>Morlaicks</hi> live generally after the mode of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> having no fix'd reſidence or retreat, they are perpetually up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſervice, and have little other ſubſiſtance but what they gain by the Wars. When they change their quarters, they carry all along with them, their Family, Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:110049:98"/>and Cattel, which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend againſt the weather by little Huts or Cabbins which they ſet up immediately. Moſt of their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers are Prieſts, which they obey very civilly, for people of their rudeneſs. They are very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and have often chang'd their ſides, but the cruelty of a late <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Boſnia,</hi> who brake his promiſes with them, has ſo exaſperated them, as I am told, they are come over wholly to the <hi>Venetian,</hi> and given him no ſmall corroboration: for though they are but as it were Voluntiers, they ſecure the Plains, open the paſſages of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, make continual incurſions into their Countrey, and keep the Enemy in a perpetual alarm.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Capelets</hi> (whom I have mentioned before) are more civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized than theſe, and not at all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour in their courage. They
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:110049:98"/>have alwayes been very faithfull to this Republick, and are imploy'd by them very frequently as Guards to the Magiſtrates, in the ſame manner as the <hi>Swiſſes</hi> are in <hi>France.</hi> They are born and brought up in an implacable antipathy againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> (which may be compar'd to that betwixt the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Spaniard</hi>) for they cannot forget they are deſcended from thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Souldiers, who under the Command of the incomparable <hi>Scanderbeg,</hi> perform'd ſo many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exploits, routed ſo many of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Armies, and fill'd the great <hi>Amurath</hi> both with indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deſpair.</p>
                  <p>There is little difference (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in their Turban) betwixt their habit and the <hi>Turks,</hi> when they come to be of any conſiderable age they let their Beards grow: they are very curious in their hair, wear
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:110049:99"/>it very long behind, but cut it and trim it before. And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the opinion the <hi>Venetian</hi> has of them, they are never al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to be in any conſiderable bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but diſtinguiſh'd into free Companies, and kept alwayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, that by dividing the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity into ſeveral hands, (which would be united in one man, were it kept in a Regimental way) they might render them leſs dangerous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Of their general Rules and Maximes in War.</head>
                  <p>THey never create any enemies to themſelves, and when they cannot avoid them, they will
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:110049:99"/>never quarrel with above one at a time, chooſing rather to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate with one, than to be driven to a diviſion of their Army, when they are engaged in a War. They have a greater eſteem for the <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montani,</hi> or <hi>Northern</hi> Souldiers, than for the <hi>Italian,</hi> there being but very few of them either Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers or Regiments to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, whereas they refuſe not any price almoſt for the ſervice of the other.</p>
                  <p>Beſides the bravery and courage, which is much more eminent and conſpicuous among the Septentrio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Souldiers, than thoſe of the warmer and more effeminate Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, without doubt they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother reaſon of no leſs weight and authority, for theſe people being ſo remote from their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, and paſſing ſo many Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Seas, cannot hope for any
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:110049:100"/>ſupplies from home, ſhould they deſign any thing for themſelves: whereas ſhould they entertain any Forces from their neighbouring Princes, who knows what plots and conſpiracies may be manag'd privately amongſt a throng of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and Officers rais'd in their Territories, and how far they may prevail towards the ſubverſion of the State.</p>
                  <p>In their extremities indeed they throw themſelves ſometimes into the arms of their allies, yet it is with ſuch caution, they never ſuffer them to be either ſo numerous, or well armed, as to give them appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion. A great ſupply to them is no leſs dreadfull than an Enemy, for when-ever they be conſiderable, they begin to be jealous and afraid of them. If they have receiv'd any numbers extraordinary of late years our of <hi>France,</hi> 'tis more to terrifie
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:110049:100"/>the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Officers with the name of the <hi>French,</hi> than any deſign they had to make uſe of them long, and this has been ſufficiently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by the ſucceſs.</p>
                  <p>Were they as well provided with them, as they are with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſaries for the War, it would be no great difficulty for them to over-power their enemies, for it is almoſt a prodigie to behold the vaſt Piles of Ammunition heap'd up in their Arſenal: in one ſingle Gallery there are arms e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for thirty thouſand men, by which pattern one may gueſs at the reſt. They have three thouſand men continually at work there, and they have ſuch multitudes of Canon, they are forc'd to pile them up three rowes high above one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, in a great large Hall they have built on purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Their Frontier Towns are as
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:110049:101"/>well furniſh'd as the Arſenal, and when they are in any apprehenſion of a ſiege, they take ſuch excellent order, they have all things in the ſame plenty as in times of peace. Their greateſt force being upon the Sea, and moſt of their Garriſons upon the Coaſts, they put in what ſupplies they think good without interruption, and their Galleys re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enforce what places they pleaſe. At the ſiege of <hi>Cataro</hi> they did the Enemy ſo much miſchief with their Canon, that they ſecured the Town in ſpite of forty thouſand men, and the <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Boſnia</hi> at the head of them, and defended it, though they had made a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble breach, and aſſaulted it with eight thouſand <hi>Janizaries</hi> and <hi>Spaihis,</hi> which were the flower of their Army, our <hi>Cuiraſſiers</hi> throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves into the Trenches, with their Pikes in their hands,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:110049:101"/>and making them good during the whole Leaguer: if <hi>Don Camilla Gonzague</hi> had acted alone, or the General <hi>Bernardo</hi> had anſwer'd his experience, our ſucceſs had been much better, and they had not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd upon us as they did; but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience muſt be given to the Commander in chief.</p>
                  <p>To engage and retain the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Officers to their ſervice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their ordinary pay they give them certain Penſions, which they call <hi>Conduct-money,</hi> and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it according to the time of their ſervice, which ſometimes amounts to a conſiderable ſumme; a thing that works much with ſuch as are devoted to their intereſt: yet for all theſe advancements, their Souldiers are not very true to them, they treating them with ſo much pride and inequality, that unleſs they will utterly renounce their own
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:110049:102"/>intereſt, and live as recluſely as in a Monaſtery, the Town is not ſecure where they are in Garriſon. There are few perſons of quality in their pay, which have not ſufficient reaſon to complain of this uſage, and amongſt the reſt, that honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Commander <hi>Monſieur Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monville,</hi> who was (as a man may ſay) born in their Armies, and would have died there before he would have forſaken them, had they not been ſo inſufferably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull. I can tell very well how much he ſuffer'd by his modeſty, and though he was ſo tender of their honour as never to complain, I am ſure he was not inſenſible of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice he receiv'd. 'Tis one of their Maximes, not to make too much of any man of extraordinary experience or eſteem. <hi>Gildas</hi> was the man for their turn, their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Careſſes being for thoſe who
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:110049:102"/>have qualifications ſufficient to execute their Orders, but not to pry too far into the intrigues of their State.</p>
                  <p>Thus Sir have I preſented you, with what a man of my ſmall age and experience was able to collect, during my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in forreign parts. Though the Style participates nothing of the Dialect of the Court, or the politeneſs of our Language, yet being writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten like a Souldier, I made no ſcruple to direct it to a Prince, who is reſolv'd to be ſo whilſt his age will permit him. For ſuch errors as have paſs'd ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Preſs, or my Pen, I humbly beg your excuſe, as proceeding from a perſon more ambitious of doing, than ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well, my greateſt aim and moſt paſſionate deſign being nothing
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:110049:103" rendition="simple:additions"/>but to dedicate my life to your ſervice, and that little experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I have been able to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire in the Wars of the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="197" facs="tcp:110049:103"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
